<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>musings</title><description>&lt;span class="tag"&gt;design&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="tag"&gt;code&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="tag"&gt;journalism&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="tag"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="tag"&gt;life&lt;/span&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/</link><generator>Ghost 0.5</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2015 00:09:56 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://julia67.github.io/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>No surprises please</title><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a retrospective on a project gone wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, CIR published a &lt;a href="https://www.revealnews.org/article/new-mexico-thrives-on-nuclear-bomb-despite-us-pledge-to-reduce-arsenal/"&gt;big investigation on the nuclear weapons industry&lt;/a&gt;. The report includes three interactive graphics: two slippy maps and a timeline of sorts. The launch was far from perfect – I wrote a 2,000-word internal report on everything that went wrong and how to avoid similar issues next time – and I wanted to riff on some those topics here as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, a little background information. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without getting too specific, the main problem with the launch was that the graphics didn't display on initial page load. The underlying cause was that the SSL implementation on revealnews.org prevented &lt;a href="https://github.com/nprapps/pym.js"&gt;Pym&lt;/a&gt; from loading, and differences between our testing and production environments prevented anyone from noticing the issue before the article went live. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not good. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, no one at CIR has authorization to fix issues with the server because the website is managed by an outside firm. As such, we couldn't resolve the real problem and had to resort to hotfixes. For two of the graphics, I could simply swap out Pym for static iframes, which wasn't a huge deal. On the other hand, my &lt;a href="https://www.revealnews.org/article/a-revolving-door-in-the-nuclear-weapons-industry/"&gt;Revolving Door&lt;/a&gt; graphic was very vertically variable – and it relied heavily on Pym. I had to actually rewrite all the code to make it work directly in Wordpress' text editor, which is ugly as hell and horrific from a maintainability perspective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, not good. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I got the hotfixes in place fairly quickly and no one died. &lt;em&gt;But the fun doesn't stop there.&lt;/em&gt; We also identified a handful of smaller bugs with the slippy maps post-launch that can be traced back to two main issues with our development and editorial processes (the real topic of this post):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incomplete Requirements Gathering  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insufficient QA Testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id="1incompleterequirementsgathering"&gt;1. Incomplete Requirements Gathering&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slippy map graphics were both designed to be full-screen desktop applications. They were built as stand-alone applications and had lots of features that come along with stand-alone apps – like internal scrolling, anchor links, full window width and height, a vertical sidebar area, and external linkage. They were very obviously supposed to function &lt;em&gt;on their own&lt;/em&gt; rather than embedded in an article page. (They were also never optimized for mobile, but that's another story.) And yet, where can you find these apps? Embedded in an article. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This illustrates a fundamental misunderstanding of requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm sure the graphics would've been designed differently if it had been clear from the beginning that the intent was to publish the graphics inside the story instead of as a supporting stand-alone app. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, here's a list of things to clarify with your editors &lt;em&gt;at the beginning&lt;/em&gt; of a project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What's the objective for this graphic?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Mark all that apply. If more than one, please specify priority.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provide additional information that &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt; in the report&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Display information from the report in an alternative way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide a tool for the public to use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make something "fun" or "delightful"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get clicks on social media&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where will the graphic run?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Mark all that apply. If more than one, please specify priority.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Embedded in an article on our main website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In its own page on our main website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As an entirely separate app, not on the main site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embedded in an article on partner websites&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When is the story running?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Please choose one.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;This week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other, please specify &amp;#95;&amp;#95;&amp;#95;&amp;#95;&amp;#95;&amp;#95;&amp;#95;&amp;#95;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answering questions like these will help ensure everyone is on the same page from the beginning. This allows the news apps folks to produce the right kind of product, and it helps set editors' expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="2insufficientqatesting"&gt;2. Insufficient QA Testing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stemming from the requirements problem comes insufficient QA testing. In the case of this nukes project, almost all of the editing and testing happened while the graphics were still in their stand-alone form. They had been cycling through the editorial process since April. The marching order to embed the graphics in an article page didn't happen until July. By then, all involved were experiencing testing burnout, we lost our slippy map developer (He's busy being awesome at &lt;a href="http://www.sfchronicle.com/"&gt;The Chronicle&lt;/a&gt; now!), and details were overlooked. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, no one at the organization had identified the discrepancies between the preview and production environments for revealnews.org – so when we &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; testing, we weren't testing the right things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The obvious solution is, firstly, to identify the appropriate testing procedures to more closely replicate our production environment. And secondly, it would be helpful to hold off on significant review of graphics until they are in the correct format, presented in exactly the same way they will be published. That could help save everyone from burning out too early and overlooking obvious bugs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="inconclusion"&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt like these graphics were handled with too editorial a focus. There were no official requirements, no set design process, no project checkpoints, no meetings, no defined testing strategy, no integration process. But at the end of the day, we were dealing with code and we should have approached it as such. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We need to approach the creation of our interactive graphics as technology products with legitimate development processes in place.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way we can document different procedures (like how to test things appropriately) and define workflows for design, development, testing, and deployment. We can make sure the right people are included and consulted at the right times in the process, and we can identify and resolve pain points earlier and more comprehensively. We can present our best work without delay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now that there's attention on the issue, we can take steps to improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fun aside! Today also birthed the best and worst backhanded compliment I've ever received:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Yours is less sophisticated, but it looks far better on mobile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/no-surprises-please/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">9b328356-ebae-4ebb-a3d3-8e3521d09540</guid><category>retrospective</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 01:48:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>#SRCCON: Feeling Inspired</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//srccon.org"&gt;SRCCON&lt;/a&gt; was last week, and it was awesome. Good discussion. Good coffee. Good times. I've come to really enjoy these news nerd "reunions" of sorts – it's fun to see everyone I don't get to work with on a daily basis and put faces to names of people from the OpenNews community calls and Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the sessions I went to were definitely engaging, although I was a little surprised by the lack of technical knowledge-sharing. I think the most concrete thing I learned was how to play "Magic the Gathering" – not that that was a problem!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, the shortage of technical discussion was far outweighed by the incredible amount of brainstorming that happened around various industry issues. I wanted to take a little time to comment on a few of these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="digitalworkflowprocesses"&gt;Digital Workflow Processes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/MaryJoWebster"&gt;MaryJo Webster&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/cjsinner"&gt;C.J. Sinner&lt;/a&gt; led an awesome and quite necessary – even overdue? – session called "Let’s Create an Ideal Digital Workflow." Session participants broke into groups and discussed one of my most favorite things in the whole world: project management. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the truth. Yes, I am a dork.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project management is so, so important for technical projects – and yes, technical projects &lt;em&gt;in journalism&lt;/em&gt; are still technical projects, and editorial processes should be adapted accordingly. (TBH, the lack of true project management is the main thing that's been driving me crazy during my fellowship. I realize now that I was quite spoiled in previous jobs where I worked with some extremely talented PMs – on teams that had concrete processes in place.) I think there's a lot of opportunity for newsrooms to adopt some basic project management practices from other industries that would significantly improve our digital workflows. I'll go into detail at another time – but at the moment, I'll leave you with the process we discussed during the session itself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Document project objectives  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify roles and responsibilities (&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Responsibility_assignment_matrix"&gt;RASCI&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kickoff: Establish project management/communication tools and set deadlines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build prototype&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iterate with user testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discuss lessons learned&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this the &lt;em&gt;exact&lt;/em&gt; workflow I'd champion? Nope. It's missing a few key pieces (like design and QA, for example) but it's a decent start. I'd love to see more discussions on this topic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;This digital workflow session is fabulous. Project management makes me so happy. Thanks &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/MaryJoWebster"&gt;@MaryJoWebster&lt;/a&gt; for facilitating. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/srccon?src=hash"&gt;#srccon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Julia Smith (@julia67) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67/status/614201794671947776"&gt;June 25, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(If you're interested in seeing the other workflows from the SRCCON session, &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1S6ms4pAMSlNpl8icrTtsHpxOpNldYWQkXQOSSwEd5UM/edit?pli=1&amp;amp;overridemobile=true"&gt;read the official session notes&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="ethicsofuxdinjournalism"&gt;Ethics of UXD in Journalism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fellow fellow &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/livlab"&gt;Livia Labate&lt;/a&gt;, along with &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/JoeGermuska"&gt;Joe Germuska&lt;/a&gt;, facilitated an awesome discussion about maintaining journalistic integrity while designing user experiences for news products (stories, websites, apps, interactives, etc.). &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1r9L0pAknMVub0MX82-KYnk71k3ZPiei_9dO6yEBPKZc/edit"&gt;Read the transcript&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The session, "Journalistic Objectivity and User-Centered Design," posed the following question: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There used to be a concept of objective truth, and news saw its job as presenting it to people. If you are focusing on users, does that still work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prompt generated more questions from the participants:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where does objectivity meet with transparency?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where does the conflict happen?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What stories are worth telling?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where is the divide between UI and content? &lt;em&gt;Is there a divide?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of this boiled down to the idea that developing a news platform or product may not necessarily be journalistic by nature and falls in a different category than creating news content, which &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; inherently journalistic and should abide by classical ideals including objectivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vocal opponent to this idea was ProPublica's &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/kleinmatic"&gt;Scott Klein&lt;/a&gt;, who said, "I disagree strongly with the notion that there is a separation between these concerns in newsroom – that there is a thing called 'actual journalism' and then something else that is a 'product.' I think it’s the wrong framing. We’re all journalists doing this work. You have the responsibilities that journalists have."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe a difference exists between the UI and the content, but I don't think this difference excuses product designers from journalistic responsibility. An example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Color.&lt;/strong&gt; Color has meaning (green = good, red = bad, etc.), so the colors in an interface shouldn't compromise the objectivity of the product's content. 
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acceptable design decision:&lt;/strong&gt; User research shows that people will click a blue button over any other color – so you choose to use the color blue to indicate action items within your interface. These action items include things like "read more" buttons and sortable table headers and don't affect the meaning of the article or data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problematic design decision:&lt;/strong&gt; If you, as a designer, are working on a graphic and decide to use a red color scale because you want to imply that something is subjectively bad, you're editorializing the data and using design to influence the user in a problematic way. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My stance: &lt;strong&gt;Design isn't inherently journalistic &lt;em&gt;until it becomes so&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; As such, UI/UX/product designers need to use their powers for good.  This is true for news website design, but it's especially true for things like news apps and interactive graphics. The designer's focus should be on creating the best user experience (guide people to click the right things, find the important information, get where they're trying to go), but in doing so, designers need to be conscious of their choices and make every effort to avoid design decisions that would affect the objectivity of the editorial content contained within their product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="mobileembraceit"&gt;Mobile: Embrace it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/aboutaaron"&gt;Aaron Williams&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/zhoyoyo"&gt;Youyou Zhou&lt;/a&gt; and I facilitated a session on improving interactives and data visualizations for mobile devices. I provided some resources &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/julia67/data-viz-for-all/"&gt;on Github&lt;/a&gt;, and participants updated &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//etherpad.mozilla.org/srccon2015-mobile-dataviz"&gt;this etherpad&lt;/a&gt; with ideas from their small-group discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I was pretty happy with how the session turned out, but I do have one major topic I'd like to discuss further: &lt;strong&gt;Building graphics for mobile doesn't have to be hellish.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, much of the session's commentary about designing for mobile was negative, as illustrated in tweets like this one, which received a disheartening amount of attention: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&amp;quot;One of the solutions we have for doing interactives on mobile is: don&amp;#39;t.&amp;quot; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/srccon?src=hash"&gt;#srccon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Heather Billings (@hbillings) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hbillings/status/614537795365941248"&gt;June 26, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;That's a pretty standard reaction. And, sure, ensuring interactives work well on mobile is complex and is too often an afterthought – &lt;em&gt;but it doesn't need to be this way&lt;/em&gt;. That's why we wanted to do this session: to get people thinking about mobile and provide them with &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/julia67/data-viz-for-all/"&gt;resources&lt;/a&gt; (examples, design patterns, code snippets, and inspiration) to make building mobile interactives easier and more effective. And we, the news nerd community, need to do a better job building open-source tools and frameworks with mobile in mind. "Mobile-first" may be a good philosophy to adopt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my part, I will continue to update the &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/julia67/data-viz-for-all/"&gt;Data Viz for All&lt;/a&gt; repo – and I invite others to contribute!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;going to refer back to this all the time: &lt;a href="https://t.co/7Limy51E5l"&gt;https://t.co/7Limy51E5l&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#10;&amp;#10;thanks &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/aboutaaron"&gt;@aboutaaron&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67"&gt;@julia67&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zhoyoyo"&gt;@zhoyoyo&lt;/a&gt;! &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/srccon?src=hash"&gt;#srccon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Priya Krishnakumar (@priyakkumar) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/priyakkumar/status/614546634291200002"&gt;June 26, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/srccon-inspiration/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">ab76dcaf-89a9-4d9c-a25c-46386001c835</guid><category>opennews</category><category>conf</category><category>srccon</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 04:48:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tinkering with Twitter's API</title><description>&lt;p&gt;OpenNews brought all of us Knight-Mozilla fellows to Minneapolis a day early for a low-key, pre-SRCCON hack day. The theme of the event was "Quant Selfish," so the goal was to make something out of personal data related to whichever topic seemed interesting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/kavyasukumar"&gt;Kavya&lt;/a&gt; and I thought it might be fun to play with the Twitter API. The idea was to get a list of unrequited Twitter friendships – the accounts you follow that never returned the favor. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Drumroll, please...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inspired by all those Twitterfolk who don't follow you back...now...without further ado...we present to you:&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//kavyasukumar.com/apps/yunofollow/follow.html"&gt;YUNOFOLLOW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;and &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/julia67/yuno"&gt;its undocumented GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;...and the crowd goes wild!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/07/yuno.jpg" alt=""&gt;
&lt;span class="caption"&gt;Here we have all 383 of my (that's &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/julia67"&gt;@julia67&lt;/a&gt;'s) unrequited friendships.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this isn't anything special or ground-breaking in the least – I had never worked with the Twitter API before, so I figured I should document the steps that went into making this Twitter app.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="makingaclientsideappwithtwitterdata"&gt;Making a client-side app with Twitter data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kavya and I only wanted to work on the front end for this, so we used &lt;a href="https://oauth.io/"&gt;oauth.io&lt;/a&gt; for OAuth integration and user management. The trickiest part was configuring the authentication piece; working with the Twitter API itself was pretty straight-forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="step1createthetwitterapplication"&gt;Step 1: Create the Twitter Application&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//apps.twitter.com"&gt;apps.twitter.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//apps.twitter.com/app/new"&gt;Create New App&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill in the application details. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Put &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://oauth.io/auth"&gt;https://oauth.io/auth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; as the callback URL.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make note of the &lt;strong&gt;Consumer Key&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Consumer Secret&lt;/strong&gt; under the &lt;strong&gt;Keys and Access Tokens&lt;/strong&gt; tab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id="step2configureoauthio"&gt;Step 2: Configure OAuth.io&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://oauth.io/"&gt;oauth.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://oauth.io/signup"&gt;Sign up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://oauth.io/signin"&gt;Sign in&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;Create an app&lt;/strong&gt;. This will generate the &lt;strong&gt;App Keys&lt;/strong&gt; (the Public Key and Private Key necessary to initialize the SDK). Find them under the &lt;strong&gt;General&lt;/strong&gt; screen.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the domain where you will host the app to the &lt;strong&gt;Domains &amp;amp; URLs whitelist&lt;/strong&gt; box on the &lt;strong&gt;General&lt;/strong&gt; screen.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;Integrated APIs&lt;/strong&gt; in the sidebar. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Click the &lt;strong&gt;Add API&lt;/strong&gt; button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose &lt;strong&gt;Twitter&lt;/strong&gt; from the available options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the Twitter &lt;strong&gt;Consumer Key&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Secret Key&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;from Step 1.4&lt;/em&gt; to the &lt;strong&gt;client_id&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;client_secret&lt;/strong&gt; fields. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;Try Auth&lt;/strong&gt;. If all goes well, you'll receive a success message containing the code you'll need to initialize OAuth from your app.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;OAuth.initialize('YOUR OAUTH.IO PUBLIC KEY GOES HERE');  
OAuth.popup('twitter').done(function(result) {  
    console.log(result);
    // do some stuff with result
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id="step3writesomecode"&gt;Step 3: Write some code&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include the oauth.io script on the page. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script src="scripts/dist/oauth.js"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initialize OAuth. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;OAuth.initialize('YOUR OAUTH.IO PUBLIC KEY GOES HERE');&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//docs.oauth.io/#authorize-with-a-popup"&gt;Authorize the app&lt;/a&gt; and save the result to a javascript object that will make HTTP calls to the Twitter API.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var provider = 'twitter';  
OAuth.popup(provider)  
.done(function(result) { // OAuth worked as expected
    twitterObj= result; 
    twitterObj.me()
    .done(function (response) { // Twitter user exists
        console.log('You're on Twitter!');
        console.log('Name: ', response.name);
        console.log(response.raw);
    })
    .fail(function (err) { // Twitter user wasn't found
        console.log(err); 
    });
})
.fail(function (err) { // OAuth didn't work
    console.log(err); 
});

$('button').click(function(){
    var friendsURL = 'https://api.twitter.com/1.1/friends/ids.json';
    twitterObj.get(friendsURL).done(function(data) {
        friendsIDs = data.ids;
    }).fail(function(err) {
        console.log(err);
    });
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's about it. We've identified a handful of issues with our code (which we wrote rather hastily) – but as this was just for fun, we're probably not going to fix anything. The goal was to identify our unrequited friendships – and identify them we did! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you're interested in trying something like this, definitely check out the &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//docs.oauth.io/"&gt;oauth.io docs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://dev.twitter.com/rest/public"&gt;Twitter API docs&lt;/a&gt;. Also, &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/hyper_linda"&gt;Linda&lt;/a&gt; found a &lt;a href="https://github.com/sferik/t"&gt;cool command line tool&lt;/a&gt; that does essentially the same thing – it's pretty spiffy if you're into that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/tinkering-with-twitters-api/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a79e63fd-6207-4ceb-b140-eea4ddc091e8</guid><category>opennews</category><category>tutorial</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2015 07:04:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Fourth Month</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Month No. 4 was busy...and pretty decent overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a few graphics published on &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//revealnews.org"&gt;revealnews.org&lt;/a&gt;. I attended a couple great conferences. I mentored some people. Another one of my session proposals was accepted. &lt;em&gt;AND&lt;/em&gt; I started building some actual tools that (I hope) will be useful for CIR and the rest of the data journalism community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, I do wish I had more assignments at CIR. I've been feeling underutilized, and I'd really like to be designing and building &lt;em&gt;systems&lt;/em&gt; rather than one-off graphics. Hopefully I can find my way onto a bigger project – or at the very least pick up some additional smaller ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="events"&gt;Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="visualizedpoliticaldata"&gt;Visualized: Political Data&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-fourth-month/../visualized-political-data/"&gt;I wrote about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="googleio2015"&gt;Google I/O 2015&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/io2015-note-dump/"&gt;I took some notes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="mentoringstanfordstudents"&gt;Mentoring Stanford Students&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a day at Stanford helping Cheryl Phillips’ computer science and journalism students design their data visualization projects. It was a cool experience, and I'm grateful for the opportunity to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="projects"&gt;Projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id="publishedwherecanyoucarryaconcealedguninpublic"&gt;Published: Where can you carry a concealed gun in public?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-fourth-month/../the-third-month/#supersecretprojectno2"&gt;Super-Secret Project No. 2&lt;/a&gt; that I mentioned last month.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//www.revealnews.org/article/the-right-to-bear-arms-in-public-how-courts-have-ruled-so-far/#us_map"&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/06/us-map.jpg" alt="" title=""&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check it out:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//www.revealnews.org/article/the-right-to-bear-arms-in-public-how-courts-have-ruled-so-far/#us_map"&gt;U.S. Map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project strengths:&lt;/strong&gt;
I’m pretty happy with how this project turned out, especially from the technical implementation side of things. It’s quite small for an interactive (~157KB, almost half of which comes from Reveal web fonts and analytics); it’s responsive; it provides a tailored experience for touch devices; and the data is completely accessible via the keyboard &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; screen readers. I think it’s a good stab at making interactive graphics usable for a broader audience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opportunities for improvement:&lt;/strong&gt;
I don’t love this interactive from a news value perspective – it's a bit superficial since most of the data isn’t geographic. Also, the addition of the court locations was a (very) late feature request, so that portion of the graphic doesn't work particularly well on mobile devices, just due to time constraints. There's definitely room to improve the newsroom's digital workflow processes; I have some ideas that I'll elaborate on at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="publishedcaliforniasconcealedgunpermitsbycounty"&gt;Published: California's Concealed Gun Permits by County&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;These interactives were part of &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-fourth-month/../the-third-month/#supersecretprojectno3"&gt;Super-Secret Project No. 3&lt;/a&gt; I mentioned last month.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//www.revealnews.org/article/want-to-carry-a-concealed-gun-live-in-sacramento-not-san-francisco/#ca_map"&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/06/cali-map.jpg" alt="California Map" width="260px" style="float:right;margin:10px 0 20px 20px;padding:10px;left:30%;"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check 'em out:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//www.revealnews.org/article/want-to-carry-a-concealed-gun-live-in-sacramento-not-san-francisco/#ca_map"&gt;Choropleth Map&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//www.revealnews.org/article/want-to-carry-a-concealed-gun-live-in-sacramento-not-san-francisco/"&gt;Interactive Table&lt;/a&gt; (scroll down a bit)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project strengths:&lt;/strong&gt;
The graphics are lightweight and performant; the data is (mostly) accessible; the styles are on-brand; and the user experience on mobile isn't terrible. I also wrote all the interactivity in vanilla javascript, so the graphics are depedency-free, which is nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opportunities for improvement:&lt;/strong&gt;
A few notes on deadlines: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deadlines are important.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deadlines only work when they're communicated.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deadlines shouldn't move – they especially shouldn't move &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For these graphics, I had a bunch of accessibility enhancements I hoped to get in place before publication, but when (on June 11) the deadline moved from Tuesday, June 16 to Friday, June 12...certain features were cut. Ambigious deadlines are worthless – they don't allow people to appropriately prioritize their work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;/rant&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, now I'm trying to build some SVG generation tools that will automatically include accessiblility features (tab indexes, keyboard events, etc.) so that developers can include AT enhancements in their graphics without needing to budget extra time to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="awaitingpublicationsupersecretprojectno1"&gt;Awaiting Publication: Super-Secret Project No. 1&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the same &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-fourth-month/../the-third-month/#supersecretprojectno1"&gt;Super-Secret Project No. 1&lt;/a&gt; that I talked about last month. I finished it around mid-May, but I'm not sure when it's scheduled for publication.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="newprojectaccessiblesvggenerator"&gt;New Project: Accessible SVG Generator&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I mentioned above, I'm working on a front-end tool that will generate accessible SVG graphics. It'll be more of a resource for UI folks and ambitious reporters rather than back-end devs. I'm excited about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="news"&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My session proposal on SVG animation was accepted for &lt;a href="https://nejsconf.com/"&gt;NEJSConf&lt;/a&gt;. It's a single-track conference, so that'll be a new and exciting experience for me. This conference is also going to be awesome because: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's at the &lt;a href="http://www.omahazoo.com/"&gt;zoo&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/beep"&gt;@beep&lt;/a&gt; is the keynote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I get to return to Homaha for it. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all good things.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/the-fourth-month/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">3d1885eb-8d5e-4353-9b89-e5d81dde7d56</guid><category>opennews</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2015 23:43:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>#IO2015: Note Dump</title><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Select session notes from &lt;a href="https://events.google.com/io2015/"&gt;Google I/O 2015&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="keynotewatchhttpsyoutube7vfigmdsme"&gt;Keynote (&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/7V-fIGMDsmE"&gt;Watch&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="androidm"&gt;Android M&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;App Permissions&lt;/strong&gt; – You can choose which permissions you can agree to. Defers asking until the point in the UX process when the permission is needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chrome Custom Tabs&lt;/strong&gt; – Resolves existing UX issues surrounding in-app browsers/webviews/native browsers. With Custom Tabs, the web view will open over the top of the app and inherit all of Chrome's features – security, passwords, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;App Linking&lt;/strong&gt; – Adds a namespace to the android manifest for verified links – so links are incorporated directly into the platform so they always open in the right application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile Payments&lt;/strong&gt; – Android Pay promises better UX, more security than Google Wallet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fingerprint Support&lt;/strong&gt; – Use fingerprint to authorize Android Pay transactions. Device unlock. Open authentication APIs so devs can incorporate fingerprint support to their own apps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Power &amp;amp; Charging&lt;/strong&gt; – Doze. Uses motion detection to put device into deeper sleep state. 2X performance improvements. The device can now act as charger for other devices with reverse USB.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UX Enhancements&lt;/strong&gt; – Better word selection and context menus. Direct share, simplified volume controls.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="androidwear"&gt;Android Wear&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1,500 watch faces for Android Wear &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Glanceable, actionable, effortless – all interactions should be this way, just like checking the time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always on screens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wrist gestures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emoji recognizer – hand-draw emojis on the screen, and the watch will recognize the shape of drawing and translate it into emoji&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New launcher&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More than 4,000 apps have been developed for Android Wear so far&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="projectbrillomoreinfohttpsdevelopersgooglecombrillo"&gt;Project Brillo (&lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/brillo/"&gt;More Info&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brillo extends Android to connected devices for easy integration with your smartphone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weave is the standard IoT protocol that connects the phone to the device to the cloud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="googlenow"&gt;Google Now&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goals:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Understand context (100m places, Natural language processing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide answers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take action&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now on Tap
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provides in-context assistance without leaving the app you’re currently using&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="googlephotos"&gt;Google Photos&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pinch view to change time criteria&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Private auto organization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Groups photos of the same person over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unlimited storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="globalefforts"&gt;Global Efforts&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's a ton of low end phones in emerging markets, perhaps more than high end devices in established areas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Translate – In emerging markets, the phone may be a person's first computer. Projected 1.2 billion smartphones by 2016.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goal – Remove barriers of smartphone adoption with &lt;strong&gt;AndroidOne&lt;/strong&gt;. Create better devices for emerging markets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issues – Connectivity. Data. Speed. Size. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimized search results – 4x faster, 80% smaller data transfer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offline support for search results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offline maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="developertools"&gt;Developer Tools&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Android Studio 1.3 – faster build speeds, full C++ support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Polymer 1.0 – material design web components&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cocoapods  – import google analytics, maps, etc into xcode for iOS development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud Test Labs for mobile app testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firebase – build an app worrying about the back end, provides asset management, authentication&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;App indexing – index app content in Google search results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud messaging – adding iOS support, topic subscriptions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mobile web – push notifications, add to home screen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Universal app campaigns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google play – conversion funnel snapshot, listing experiments (like optimizely, including app icon tests)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="virtualreality"&gt;Virtual Reality&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New Google Cardboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expeditions – program for virtual reality field trips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionaccessibledesignguidelinesreadmorehttpgooglecomaccessibility"&gt;Session: Accessible Design Guidelines (&lt;a href="http://google.com/accessibility"&gt;Read more&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="whyisnteverythingaccessible"&gt;Why isn't everything accessible?&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it seems really hard.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="useheuristicevaluationtoimprovedesignsforaccessibility"&gt;Use heuristic evaluation to improve designs for accessibility&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on usability within accessibility
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Fonts can be enlarged&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Critical audio elements/sounds include text alternative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Touch targets should be large enough for a low mobility user&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="improvingthedesignprocess"&gt;Improving the design process&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diversify your personas &lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;include persons for low vision, low mobility, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;define the user journey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what are the steps to complete the task?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluate and prioritize &lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;choose your participant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;have a person with a disability help you or simulate your user's perspective&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organize the equipment &lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Acquire and learn the technology&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conduct the evaluation  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capture your process &lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Record the steps the user takes to complete the task&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share and inspire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionaccessiblewebcomponentsrepohttpgithubcomwebcomponentsgoldstandardwiki"&gt;Session: Accessible Web Components (&lt;a href="http://github.com/webcomponents/gold-standard/wiki"&gt;Repo&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web components are exciting but create some challenges for accessibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 in 7 will experience a disability in their life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://github.com/webcomponents/gold-standard/wiki"&gt;http://github.com/webcomponents/gold-standard/wiki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a checklist for development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start with the keyboard.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Focusable. Put elements into the tab order. Add tabindex="0" attribute to give elements keyboard focus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visible focus state. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keyboard support. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test semantics with a screen reader.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Declared semantics. Look into accessibility nodes. Semantics: role, value, state. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Labels. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ARIA (accessible rich internet applications). The attribute "aria-label" can be added to elements that don't need a visual label. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Redundant color. Don't use color alone to distinguish between different elements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sufficient contrast. 4.5 minimum contrast ratio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developers need to build their own accessibility nodes into polymer web components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionadaptivedesignwithmaterial"&gt;Session: Adaptive Design with Material&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How we talk about taking about UI:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;To identify an element, we describe its structure, behavior, position, and permanence.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Breakpoints:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Show a single level of content hierarchy under 600px.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1600px is the max width with Material.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grids create limitations for a layout, and within those limitations come opportunities. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the new Chrome Developer Tools devices tab for testing layouts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionnextgenerationmobilewebwatchhttpsyoutubeizzdhtup5qg"&gt;Session: Next Generation Mobile Web (&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/iZZdhTUP5qg"&gt;Watch&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="reach"&gt;Reach&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reach of content – rediscovering the superpower of the web&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1B+ Chrome users&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="performance"&gt;Performance&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When is a site performant enough? When the user can't perceive it. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;strong&gt;RAIL&lt;/strong&gt; conceptual framework.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; – Reaction Time &amp;lt;100ms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt; – Animation Time &amp;lt;16.67ms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; – Idle Time &amp;lt;50ms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L&lt;/strong&gt; – Load Time &amp;lt;1s&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="engagement"&gt;Engagement&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The missing piece&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push notifications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add to homescreen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offline support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sessiondevelopingappswithfirebasewatchhttpsyoutubewf9hzcqqi7a"&gt;Session: Developing Apps with Firebase (&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/wf9hZcqQI7A"&gt;Watch&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.firebase.com"&gt;Firebase&lt;/a&gt; is a cloud-based service that can “power your app's backend, including data storage, user authentication, static hosting, and more.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sky news UK election map was built on Firebase&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New at I/O – mobile offline support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionmakebelievedesigningforvr"&gt;Session: Make Believe: Designing for VR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtual reality is coming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flow: Visual immersion --&gt; tracking --&gt; input --&gt; VR &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessibility:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;VR viewers anyone can make (Cardboard viewers)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visual immersion:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Focus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depth perception&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Latency&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different lenses for each eye:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Pincushion distortion in one, barrel distortion in the other&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Input without controllers:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Capacitive triggers&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lessons learned:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;VR is great for exploring spaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great for empathy&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Core pillars in VR game design:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Agency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comfort (high fps, g force only down, positional reference, blink movement, forward only game, no screen freeze, only player movement, snap turning, static skybox, large cockpit)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Progression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tactile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Empowerment&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designing the environment
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get scale right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bug-free geometry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reward exploring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coherent world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Safe spaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Player warning&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sessiongetyourappintothegoogleindex"&gt;Session: Get your app into the Google index&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="resources"&gt;Resources:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Android and iOS app indexing: &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/io2015-note-dump/g.co/appfirstindexing"&gt;g.co/appfirstindexing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;URL Shortener: &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/io2015-note-dump/g.co/urlshortener"&gt;g.co/urlshortener&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search Console: &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/io2015-note-dump/g.co/Searchconsole"&gt;g.co/searchconsole&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;App Indexing: &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/io2015-note-dump/g.co/appindexing"&gt;g.co/appindexing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionmaterialicons"&gt;Session: Material Icons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are material icons?
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Consistent design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suitable for all platforms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suitable for all purposes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resources:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Material Icon Library – &lt;a href="http://google.com/design/icons"&gt;google.com/design/icons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the repo – &lt;a href="http://github.com/google/material-design-icons"&gt;github.com/google/material-design-icons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Icon font features:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ligatures! So cool. You can just type the name of the icon and the font will ligature itself into the desired image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standard link tag with Google Web Fonts&lt;br&gt; &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;span class="material-icons"&amp;gt;menu&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionmaterialdesignlitereadmorehttpsdevelopersgooglecomwebtoolsmaterialdesignlite"&gt;Session: Material Design Lite (&lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/web/tools/material-design-lite/"&gt;Read more&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What?&lt;/strong&gt; A CSS and JS framework to achieve the Material Design aesthetic for web apps without Polymer. Made up of three parts:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Styles:&lt;/strong&gt; colors, typography&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Components:&lt;/strong&gt; buttons, switches, form elements, tabs, menus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Templates:&lt;/strong&gt; product pages, dashboards, cards, blogs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why?&lt;/strong&gt; To bridge the gap between the material design spec and web apps. It allows developers to build web apps with standard front-end languages so they can support older browsers (and for whatever other reason). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How?&lt;/strong&gt; Code will be open sourced in github. It will be available as bundled JS and CSS, essentially like a jQuery UI replacement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Support?&lt;/strong&gt; IE9 plus for components. IE10+ for templates. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When?&lt;/strong&gt; To be released at the end of June.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preview?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.getmdl.io/"&gt;getmdl.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionreachandreengage"&gt;Session: Reach and Re-engage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push Notifications for Android and all desktop platforms (not iOS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only works on HTTPS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three APIs:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Service worker (JavaScript when tab isn't open)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push messaging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notifications&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workflow: App JS (request notification permission) --&gt; Chrome --&gt; Google cloud messaging --&gt; app server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Debug with &lt;a href="chrome://serviceworker-internals"&gt;chrome://serviceworker-internals&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Not in regular Chrome Dev Tools yet&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UX Principles:
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Only use it for really high priority things&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Track click through rate for notifications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Track when people revoke permissions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Users should demonstrate intent before sites ask for a permission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Airline example - after purchasing a ticket, show button asking if user is interested in receiving notifications, after user engage - then ask permission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow users to opt out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example, if the user wants updates on a story, they should be able to see an option to turn off notifications when they view the story again.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Recorded I/O 2015 Sessions: &lt;a href="https://events.google.com/io2015/videos"&gt;https://events.google.com/io2015/videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/io2015-note-dump/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">29f251a8-c957-40ea-9711-6d51b4b20e88</guid><category>conf</category><category>google-io</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2015 23:45:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>4 Topics from Visualized: Political Data</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I spent a couple days in DC last week so I could attend &lt;a href="http://visualized.com/politicaldata/"&gt;Visualized: Political Data&lt;/a&gt;, a one-day conference dedicated to exploring data visualizations in the context of political science, political campaigns, and political journalism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt conflicted about flying all the way from SFO to DCA for a one-day event, but since political data viz is both where I came from (working with Gallup’s opinion poll data) and where I’d potentially like to go again, I figured it would be worth it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm glad I went. I was a little disappointed that some of the slated speakers had cancelled (including Lisa Strausfeld, who I had been looking forward to seeing), but overall the sessions were engaging and insightful. I definitely picked up some good info – the highlights of which I'll share with you now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="topic1publicdataopengovernment"&gt;Topic 1: Public Data / Open Government&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derek Willis (NYT), Ryan Sibley (Sunlight Foundation), and Rebecca Williams (Data.gov) all tackled topics related to working with government data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Willis began with the example of collecting leave of absence records for congressional representatives. This is a metric that should be tracked and available but isn’t – either due to human error or bad record-keeping practices. Plus, even if we had accurate data on congressional leaves of absence, we still wouldn’t know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; a representative was absent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while it’s nice to play with government datasets, you should really be looking beyond that – combining datasets from various places and scraping data from government apps to fill in the pieces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Willis said the biggest opportunities for improvement are in: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing efficient information markets  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linking offline and online actions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving speed and accuracy in public data reporting. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out some of Willis’ projects: &lt;a href="https://theunitedstates.io/"&gt;@unitedstates&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://openelections.net/"&gt;Open Elections&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sibley went over a few of the datasets that Sunlights has opened:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="politicalinfluence"&gt;Political influence:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://realtime.influenceexplorer.com/newest-filings/#?ordering=-filing_number&amp;amp;time_range=cycle"&gt;FEC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://sunlightfoundation.com/policy/municipal_campaign_finance/"&gt;State campaign finance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://reporting.sunlightfoundation.com/lobbying/"&gt;Lobbying data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunlightfoundation.com/search/?q=revolving+door&amp;amp;order_by=1"&gt;Revolving door data&lt;/a&gt; (also see &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/visualized-political-data/OpenSecrets.org"&gt;OpenSecrets.org&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://transparencycaucus.org"&gt;Advisor Committee on Transparency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="criminaljustice"&gt;Criminal justice:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://sunlightfoundation.com/criminaljustice/"&gt;Criminal justice data collection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunlightfoundation.com/blog/2015/05/01/the-benefits-of-criminal-justice-data-beyond-policing/"&gt;Bureau of Justice Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;U.S. Sentencing Commission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Local police departments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sibley also discussed some of the issues that make it hard to achieve Sunlight’s goals regarding open data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Methodologies can keep us from understanding the whole story. 
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Example: When requesting data on the cause of death by law enforcement, the CDC suppressed smaller numbers to protect individual identities.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Old technology stands in the way of improving reporting. 
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Example: Senators don’t disclose their campaign finance reports digitally at this time. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the criminal justice system, there’s no way to track individual cases over time because the police, courts, corrections, and re-entry organizations don’t share data with each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In politics, there’s no way to track all the different players. 
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Example: There is no unique ID for donations by organization, so if a company’s name changes, it’s difficult to match it with its previous name. When unique IDs are missing, it’s hard to identify which organizations are affiliated.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help resolve some of these issues, Sibley implored everyone to use the data. Demonstrated interest will lead to the release of more and better data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Williams had similar things to say regarding government data collection – sometimes government data simply isn’t properly collected, structured, public, or reusable. This is where coalitions and partnerships between the government and the private sector (like &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/visualized-political-data/freelawfounders.org"&gt;freelawfounders.org&lt;/a&gt;) become valuable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest advantage of government data is that you can vote on it. The more you can point to people losing money, the more actionable the response will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="links"&gt;Links:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://fedspendingtransparency.github.io/"&gt;http://fedspendingtransparency.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://labs.data.gov/dashboard/offices"&gt;http://labs.data.gov/dashboard/offices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="topic2maps"&gt;Topic 2: Maps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alicia Parlapiano (New York Times) and Alyson Hurt (NPR) both spoke about maps – mostly U.S. state maps. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alicia laid out four goals for representing state data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessibility  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fairness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revelation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “fairness problem” relates to how the physical size of different states can misrepresent the data by masking huge differences in population. Take national elections for example: Montana and Delaware have the same number of electoral votes (3), but when you look at a map, Montana’s size dwarfs Delaware’s, which – at a glance – leaves the impression that Montana’s votes count more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cartograms can help solve the fairness problem for electoral votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grid maps – made of squares or hexagons – are also good options when you want to show state totals without giving any one state more visual weight than another. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hurt explained that the challenge with grid maps is geographic fidelity. Consider offering context by placing a geographically accurate image next to the cartogram. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parlapiano and Hurt also emphasized that maps aren’t the only way to present state data – and they frequently aren’t even the best way. Jonathan Schwabish also touched on this point. He suggested asking four questions before choosing to make a map:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should it be a bar chart?  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should it be a scatterplot?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should it be a table?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should it simply be a sentence?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id="topic3elections"&gt;Topic 3: Elections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy Cotgreave (Tableau) and Sarah Newhall (Blue State Digital) spoke about using data visualization to engage people with political data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contgreave specifically analyzed how the U.K. media used twitter in the recent elections. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="contgreavesdiscoveries"&gt;Contgreave's discoveries:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sentiment tracking is dangerous&lt;/strong&gt; – This is especially true with Twitter because Twitter demographics are not representative of the real world. However, Twitter stats are very shareable, and people take it for granted that the data is accurate. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Polls v. actual results&lt;/strong&gt; – For the UK election, none of the polls were correct. Even though the pollsters got it wrong, the poll results still drove the party strategy, the media, the agenda. Pollsters are sometime too shocked by outliers and will massage the data too much. In the most recent elections, the outliers weren’t really outliers at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer a new question every day&lt;/strong&gt; – Play with the data and post it on a day-to-day basis because that’s what keeps people engaged. If you build out all these fancy apps for visualizing – but the data is boring – people won’t stay interested. For example, if you’re visualizing trends over time but the trend never changes, no one will care.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newhall came at it from the marketing campaign side of things. She emphasized that data does a handful of things when used to influence people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It proves what’s at stake.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It motivates people to act.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It turns defense into offense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It shapes the narrative and provides clear explanations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It informs and inspires.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="topic4dataforhumans"&gt;Topic 4: Data for Humans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jamie Chandler (George Washington University), Jonathan Schwabish (Urban Institute), and Ben Casselman (FiveThirtyEight) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="fromchandler"&gt;From Chandler:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today we have an opportunity to take data and communicate it to people in a simple, elegant way – and cut through all the talk that they get from the political world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data has been a big part of elections over the last couple cycles. We have all this data that’s being used to drive the vote, but we can also use that data in our messaging. We can communicate very complex things to the public in very simple ways. Simple data points that will shift our perception of previously held beliefs. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We’re missing the bridge between data science and communications. Politicians, CEOs, leaders rely on their gut feel 67% of the time. They’ll disregard what the data scientist recommends. Communications professionals have not be exposed to this level of sophistication [data analysis]. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the campaign world, we have to start thinking about how we connect the people who talk to the public and the people who do the analysis. Vocative is an online news agency that partners a data scientist with a journalist to mine the web for news. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we’re going to bring data into the conversation, we have to remember who the average person is. In general, only 66% are able to remember visual. Statistical literacy is generally very low. People have biases when it relates to politics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="fromschwabish"&gt;From Schwabish:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think carefully and critically about your graphics – because people will learn something from them. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix Modalities
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Example: &lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/life/culturebox/2014/10/population_map_use_our_interactive_map_to_figure_out_how_many_flyover_states.html"&gt;Equal population mapper&lt;/a&gt; from Slate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example: “The site now stores 90 million gallons of radioactive water, more than enough to fill Yankee stadium." - WashPo&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big enough, but not too big
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Super-imposing Jupiter on Earth's horizon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steve Jobs presenting the Macbook Air in an envelope&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a Soul
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Identifiable Victim Effect. We’re more likely to provide aid to an actual person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The problem with statistics is that they don’t activate our moral emotions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communicating requires connecting.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="fromcasselman"&gt;From Casselman:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reach readers who aren't data junkies? (Without disappointing the nerds)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communicate methodology? (Without convoluting the story)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reflect uncertainty? (Without sewing confusion)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Readers should be able to understand:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Where the data comes from&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limitations of the data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The assumptions and decisions we've made while working with the data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How our analysis supports our conclusions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How confident we are in this conclusions&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes the uncertainty is the story itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;More coverage of &lt;em&gt;Visualized: Political Data:&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?src=typd&amp;amp;q=%23visualizedpd"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.azavea.com/blogs/atlas/2015/05/unicorns-ducks-and-things-that-are-big-a-recap-of-visualized-political-data/"&gt;Azavea report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/visualized-political-data/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">e7dc5fd7-736e-4844-87b9-e41507859188</guid><category>conf</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2015 00:46:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Third Month</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I can hardly believe it: I stayed in California the entire month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fellowship Month No. 3 was mostly solid time in the office, which was a nice change of pace from the long conferences in March and April. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's what I was up to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="events"&gt;Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="techrakingelevatingthenews"&gt;TechRaking: Elevating the News&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CIR hosted a &lt;a href="http://www.revealnews.org/events/techraking/techraking-elevating-the-news/"&gt;drone journalism event&lt;/a&gt; in Berkeley on April 22. The day started with a panel discussion on advancements in drone technology and legislative issues, and in the afternoon everyone broke into teams to develop proposals for projects that would utilize drone technology for journalistic efforts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My team presented the winning concept for DroneHound, which would use drones to collect air samples in highly polluted areas and report the data with a mobile app. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More on the event: &lt;a href="http://www.revealnews.org/article/illegal-but-coming-soon-drones-meet-journalism-at-berkeley-techraking/"&gt;http://www.revealnews.org/article/illegal-but-coming-soon-drones-meet-journalism-at-berkeley-techraking/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Great working with you all today! &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/pawpound?src=hash"&gt;#pawpound&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/add"&gt;@add&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/morisy"&gt;@morisy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Digidave"&gt;@Digidave&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67"&gt;@julia67&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/TechRaking?src=hash"&gt;#TechRaking&lt;/a&gt; thanks &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/CIRonline"&gt;@CIRonline&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://t.co/yDztc1wxH3"&gt;pic.twitter.com/yDztc1wxH3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Lakshmi Sarah (@lakitalki) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/lakitalki/status/591084127257931776"&gt;April 23, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="smashingconf2015"&gt;SmashingConf 2015&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to Santa Monica at the tail end of April for &lt;a href="http://smashingconf.com/la-2015/"&gt;SmashingConf&lt;/a&gt;, one of Smashing Magazine's annual conferences. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-third-month/../smashingconf-notes/"&gt;I took a lot of notes&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought all the talks were really engaging, which can be tricky for multi-day, single-track conferences. (That's a lot of sitting and listening.) &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/draplin"&gt;Aaron Draplin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/andybudd"&gt;Andy Budd's&lt;/a&gt; talks were probably my favorites. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoyed being at a design event – I think sometimes the official news nerd conferences can be a little overwhelming because there are so many areas of concentration (reporting, data, coding, design, etc.), so sometimes it's nice to focus intently on one discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="projects"&gt;Projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="supersecretprojectno1"&gt;Super-Secret Project No. 1&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the same project I started working on last month, and hopefully it will be done soon. It's been a real struggle from a process perspective (project management, expectations, communication, etc.) – which makes me wonder if there are things we can do to make the design process smoother going forward. Most of my suggestions would come from the dev processes we used at my past jobs, especially when I was on an in-house UX team. I'm just not sure of the best way to incorporate those ideas into the editorial process. I need to bounce ideas off others in the newsroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="supersecretprojectno2"&gt;Super-Secret Project No. 2&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's a map! Nothing fancy, but it was nice to have a quick project to build. I believe it'll be published in early June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="supersecretprojectno3"&gt;Super-Secret Project No. 3&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's a map! This one is slightly more involved than the last. It's also set for publication in early June. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps next month I'll be able to share more details and the GitHub repos for all these. It's a little strange trying to work in the open when I'm not obliged to discuss unpublished projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="news"&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="srccon"&gt;SRCCON&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my &lt;a href="http://srccon.org"&gt;SRCCON&lt;/a&gt; session proposals was accepted, which is great. I'll be leading a discussion on &lt;a href="http://srccon.org/sessions/#proposal-112035"&gt;Lo-Fi Data Viz&lt;/a&gt; along with &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/aboutaaron"&gt;Aaron Williams&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zhoyoyo"&gt;Youyou Zhou&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="newsroomupdate"&gt;Newsroom Update&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We just found out that Aaron is leaving CIR, which is sad for us! I expect my role will evolve a bit as a result.&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Hey! Some personal news. I&amp;#39;ll be joining the &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/sfchronicle"&gt;@sfchronicle&lt;/a&gt; as its data visualization editor starting in June. Ain&amp;#39;t that something?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Aaron Williams (@aboutaaron) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/aboutaaron/status/600431407735787520"&gt;May 18, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/the-third-month/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">c8dfa080-1f15-44f3-bf0f-02bf417177db</guid><category>opennews</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 05:42:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>#SmashingConf: Note Dump</title><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;CONFERENCE NOTE DUMP! YEAH! &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;My commentary is in &lt;em&gt;italics&lt;/em&gt;. Updates are ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="stevesoudersdesignperformance"&gt;Steve Souders: Design + Performance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/souders"&gt;@souders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="trickstomarrydesignandperformance"&gt;Tricks to marry design and performance:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create small interdisciplinary teams.&lt;/strong&gt; Bring all players into the mix early in the process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Define guiding principles.&lt;/strong&gt; What's most important for producing a successful use experience? Speed is more important than design embellishment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prototype early.&lt;/strong&gt; Have designers work on individual assets. An early prototype helps identify areas where performance will likely be a challenge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implement a performance budget.&lt;/strong&gt; Surface the metrics for the team, and display a clear baseline for what's acceptable. 
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Define the most important elements on the page and define custom metrics for those elements. Use user timing API. Track when the image gets rendered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a bookmarklet to analyze page performance against your specific project metrics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Window.onload is not the best metric for analyzing performance. It's more important to optimize for above-the-fold content. Use &lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/a/webpagetest.org/docs/using-webpagetest/metrics/speed-index"&gt;SpeedIndex&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href="http://www.webpagetest.org/"&gt;WebPageTest&lt;/a&gt; for this. Also &lt;a href="https://speedcurve.com/"&gt;SpeedCurve&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="heroimagedelayhidproblem"&gt;Hero Image Delay (HID) problem&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't define giant bg images in external CSS. Inline it. Make sure hero IMG is first IMG tag in the page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Browsers promote importance of scripts and CSS over images, which blocks rendering. Use async and deferred instead of sticking scripts at the bottom of the page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="takeaways"&gt;Takeaways:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify what matters must. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prioritize ux performance. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Track custom metrics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="notafanofframeworks"&gt;Not a fan of frameworks"&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frameworks are great for prototyping, but write your own code for production. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;I agree!&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="samanthawarrenguerrilladesigntactics"&gt;Samantha Warren: Guerrilla Design Tactics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/SamanthaToy"&gt;@SamanthaToy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design systems, not pages.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Get buy-in.&lt;/strong&gt; They took their stakeholders and other teams out to events to get everyone on board with their small team's project – to define styles and make the company's various sites more consistent and on-brand.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Used atomic design to create a template&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developed a component library for front-end developers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;…and nothing changed, despite a ton of buy in. &lt;em&gt;This all sounds very familiar.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once stakeholders and affected teams realized that they actually had to change their processes, they became aggressive.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Didn't adapt tools to culture of the organization (people used Photoshop, didn't understand atomic design)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Didn't speak the language of the executive leadership. Like David and Goliath.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design problems can be organizational problems.&lt;/strong&gt; A designer's responsibility is that ideas get through, and projects get shipped. Not just to design pretty interfaces/experiences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be flexible, fast, and persistent.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Artists for inspiration:&lt;/strong&gt; Olek, Banksy, Invader…using premade sweaters, stencils, tiles - because they're fast! And reusable. They just do it; the don't ask for permission. Don't wait for an invitation to do the work you want. Or the work you need. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a strategy.&lt;/strong&gt; And tactics for use during the project. Crete a framework and break down the problem into smaller chucks. Attack those chicks with your tactics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build a robust toolbox.&lt;/strong&gt; The best tools are those you know well and can access quickly. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Map things out.&lt;/strong&gt; Use a story map/wire flow map to walk through product design &lt;em&gt;&amp;lt;-- I've always loved making these.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do what's best for the user.&lt;/strong&gt; Use style tiles to get away from having stakeholder fall in love with the look of the wireframe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speak the language.&lt;/strong&gt; $$$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be persistent.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share your experience&lt;/strong&gt; with community and your organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...She has never been successful at automating a pattern library. &lt;em&gt;…uhoh for me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="petesmartfutureofthewebis"&gt;Pete Smart: Future of the web is…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/petewsmart"&gt;@petewsmart&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The intersection of science, technology, and design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tangible.&lt;/strong&gt; Haptics. Electrostatic manipulation. Consider possible impact on: shopping, education (embodied cognition), usability (braille), communication (Skype)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adaptive.&lt;/strong&gt; Wearables. Internet of Things. Security/authentication (digital footprint, passwords). Mutation (responsive, the grid - machine learning) – analytical, personal, human (adaptive to mood). Are you in the mood for a long read or a short one? Photos or text? Avatar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invisible.&lt;/strong&gt; The web is fluid and unconstrained. Zeros and ones. Ambient interfaces. Ambient beer pong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;For interesting thought experiments reminiscent of this Future of the Web talk, watch Black Mirror. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/smashingconf?src=hash"&gt;#smashingconf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Julia Smith (@julia67) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67/status/593132177321164800"&gt;April 28, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sarasoueidanavoidingsvgpitfalls"&gt;Sara Soueidan: Avoiding SVG Pitfalls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/sarasoueidan"&gt;@SaraSoueidan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You should probably just read &lt;a href="http://sarasoueidan.com/articles/"&gt;everything Sara has ever written&lt;/a&gt;, because it is significantly better than these notes!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presentation attributes will override inherited store specified on a parent element.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;CSS overrides inline, which overrides parent attributes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CSS all: property&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CSS variables (only in FF now)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anchor tags inside the SVG will open inside SVG.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use xlink-target attribute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set xlink namespace on root SVG element&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't try to use jquery with SVG.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Certain CSS and JS characters will break inside svg (&amp;lt;, &gt;, &amp;amp;, etc.). 
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Solution: wrap CSS and js in [CDATA] block.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The viewbox. Always use it because it's super powerful. &lt;a href="http://sarasoueidan.com/demos/interactive-svg-coordinate-system/index.html"&gt;Check out the demo&lt;/a&gt;. Use a clippath to crop svg to viewbox. X and Y of clippath need to be same value as X and Y on viewbox.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CSSOM methods use coordinates of the page, not of the SVG. Use bbox methods instead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No relative positioning, because there's no box model for SVG. 
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Solution: nest svgs. This creates a new coordinate system.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

 &lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="trentwaltonarewehavingfunyet"&gt;Trent Walton: Are we having fun yet?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/TrentWalton"&gt;@TrentWalton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="perceptionvsreality"&gt;Perception vs. Reality&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is what we perceive actually the way it is?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on background or role on a project, everyone evaluates the quality of a design from a different perspective:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aesthetics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SEO&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t that anybody is right or wrong, but they’re coming at it from different places. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The web is edgeless. Organizations should seek to be edgeless as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Edgelessness means blurred lines between the disciplines that work together to make things for the web. Everyone that I’ve spoken with that’s worked on a large responsive project with a big client says that the process disrupts workflows, expectations, and work culture.” &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;– Frank Chimero, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/smashingconf-notes/“http://frankchimero.com/talks/the-webs-grain/transcript/“" target="“_blank”"&gt;The Web Grain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h6 id="howdoyoustartworkingtogetheronaproject"&gt;How do you start working together on a project?&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You prototype.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You build something from scratch, without any of the waterfall processes in place. It provides a foundation to build on top of, which can set the whole process up for success. If we’re all working on something in the browser, it helps us to see things in the same way. Our perceptions are going to be less and less compartmentalized. It shifts the way we work and the things we do from “mine” to “ours.” If we’re working together on a prototype, it’s &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; thing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If a picture is worth 1,000 words, &lt;strong&gt;a prototype is worth 1,000 meetings.&lt;/strong&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h6 id="thingstokeepinmind"&gt;Things to keep in mind&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People get really practical when you show them the code that renders something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encourages designers to dive into code. That’s when perceptions overlaps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If team members see each other as competitors, things go south quickly. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to get to the point where you see things the same way and you trust each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audience Question:&lt;/strong&gt; How is it different than design by committee? &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Answer:&lt;/strong&gt; Strong leadership. Respecting everyone’s expertise. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="kristinahalversoncontentcommunication"&gt;Kristina Halverson: Content/Communication&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content First:&lt;/strong&gt; Frequently it just isn’t successful and we’re left with products without copy at the end of the project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think about questions instead of copy.&lt;/strong&gt; Think about questions and artifacts that should happen early in your design and development process.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Why do we need this in the first place? Shouldn’t we take some time to strategically consider the things that we’re migrating?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How is it going to get done? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who’s going to do it? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What tools will you use? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When is it going to get done? Planning for caveats, turnover, other issues. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who is the content for – for your audiences or for you (about us, mission statement, etc)? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are your user personas? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where does your content currently live? How many platforms, APIs, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How often do we have to updated it? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the resources needed to update it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once the site is launched, then what happens to your content? What’s next?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;Core Strategy&lt;/strong&gt; helps us prioritize and is supported by two parts:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Substance &amp;amp; Structure:&lt;/strong&gt; Content audit, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Workflow &amp;amp; Governance:&lt;/strong&gt; What processes tools and people are going to be required to sustain this content strategy over time?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"Shift your outlook from content publication to content lifecycle. Don’t just think about helping content go live."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h6 id="discoveryprocess"&gt;Discovery process&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content audit.&lt;/strong&gt; Make a plan for what attributes you’re going to audit. Are you going to set readability standards? Standards for voice and brand appropriateness? Standards for meta tags? For accessibility? Don’t do your content audit manually; use automated tools (like Content Analysis Tool) to inventory your content. Invite the copy writer into the room so they can take an active approach in the conversations about IA and content organization. What content is there that is redundant, outdated or trivial? Is there a style guide? Review search analytics? Legal requirements? Stakeholder agendas? Content owners? Workflow and timeline considerations? Integrity of metadata? Translation requirements? Accessibility requirements?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Define the project.&lt;/strong&gt; High-level architecture. Content requirements. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don’t always need to design with copy, but know your audience. It needs to set the appropriate tone for the stakeholder you’re presenting to. Use real copy when you can.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="afterlaunch"&gt;After launch&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Care for your content. Leave your organization with an ongoing content quality plan. QA for content. Ensure editorial oversight is in place. Teach producers how to tag content appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="learnaboutadaptivecontent"&gt;Learn about adaptive content&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you deliver content responsively, getting to a state of content reuse will be key to content strategy success. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="takeaways"&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empower the writers. Make a style guide. Bring content strategy into your process. Don’t say it’s not your problem because you’re the designer or the developer – the quality of the content affects the quality of the work you produce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="zenorochacomputervision"&gt;Zeno Rocha: Computer Vision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(@zenorocha)[https://twitter.com/zenorocha]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="computervisionincludes"&gt;Computer vision includes:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Face detection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Face recognition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Autonomous robots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtual reality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Augmented reality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="github"&gt;Github:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.hitl.washington.edu/artoolkit/"&gt;Artoolkit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/kig/JSARToolKit"&gt;Jsartoolkit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://opencv.org/"&gt;Opencv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="steps"&gt;Steps:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access the camera&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Media capture and streams navigator.getUserMedia()&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reproduce captured content as &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;video&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;obtain pixel matrix, pit it on &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;canvas&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tracking algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="trackingjs"&gt;Tracking.js&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://trackingjs.com/"&gt;Tracking.js&lt;/a&gt; is a tool that "brings different computer vision algorithms and techniques into the browser environment." It has a low learning curve for front-end folks to pick up because it's 100% JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="aarondraplin"&gt;Aaron Draplin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/draplin"&gt;@draplin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This talk was too good. No notes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;So proud of my note taking skills at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/smashingconf?src=hash"&gt;#smashingconf&lt;/a&gt; until &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Draplin"&gt;@draplin&lt;/a&gt; walked up on stage... @ Casa Del Mar &lt;a href="https://t.co/V7REuYcCKE"&gt;https://t.co/V7REuYcCKE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; beckysoll (@beckysoll) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/beckysoll/status/593223295631253504"&gt;April 29, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;This is awesome &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Draplin"&gt;@Draplin&lt;/a&gt; killing it!... amazing design, super inspirational. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/smashingconf?src=hash"&gt;#smashingconf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Brady Sammons (@soulrider911) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/soulrider911/status/593209122918518784"&gt;April 29, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;I laughed. I cried. I got inspired. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Draplin"&gt;@Draplin&lt;/a&gt; stole the show at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/smashingconf?src=hash"&gt;#smashingconf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/design?src=hash"&gt;#design&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/inspiration?src=hash"&gt;#inspiration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Kris Guadarrama (@kristop) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kristop/status/593236756314501121"&gt;April 29, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Thanks for the inspiring, beautiful, hilarious talk at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/smashingconf?src=hash"&gt;#smashingconf&lt;/a&gt; Aaron. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Draplin"&gt;@Draplin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Justin Roberts (@roarked) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/roarked/status/593220929884266498"&gt;April 29, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Draplin"&gt;@Draplin&lt;/a&gt; This was easily one of the best design presentations I&amp;#39;ve ever seen in my life. Never forget your design roots! &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/smashingconf?src=hash"&gt;#smashingconf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Penny Tselikis (@penny_tselikis) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/penny_tselikis/status/593220223974551552"&gt;April 29, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="cameronmollthoughtsondesign"&gt;Cameron Moll: Thoughts on design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cameronmoll"&gt;@cameronmoll&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We make mistakes throughout our careers and think it's the end of the road. Ask yourself: When I'm 80 years old, how am I going to feel about how I handled this situation? It's not a waste if you learn from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="mentalmodels"&gt;Mental models&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mental models and intuition come into play when you approach a new experience. You expect it to work the same way as that model. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think beyond labels to break out of your own mental models. Don't just think about mobile, tablet, desktop. It's bigger than that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="responsivedesign"&gt;Responsive Design:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We assume we're delivering the best experience for it users, but your deliverable may actually break the mental model for a portion of your users. For example, Does my site's mobile version disable pinch and zoom?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't assume we know what's best for our audience.
Allow users to determine how they want to use your site. &lt;strong&gt;Elective UX.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider: zooming where content reflows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RWD is limiting because it's limited to the browser – think about how people use the app for Facebook rather than the browser version.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"The best interface is one that's in reach."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h6 id="redefiningmobile"&gt;Redefining 'Mobile'&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When we talk about mobile, make the distinction between the noun and the verb. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Step back and assess how the experiences on different devices come together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="cohesiveuxunifiedux"&gt;Cohesive UX. Unified UX.&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we create a cohesive experience across many screens? How do we form a united whole and not a mindless clone? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand context. Don't assume that every screen needs to be a discrete, unique experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Form and function. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data symmetry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="formandfunction"&gt;Form and function:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good example: Amazon. Gmail. Both keep the same look and process on different devices. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RWD is great for marketing sites, but it's a nightmare for data heavy, complex sites. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rdio doesn't even try to create an experience for mobile web – but that's OK if it was the best approach given the company's goals, resources, and user metrics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="datasymmetry"&gt;Data symmetry&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The continuity of data and workflow process among different devices. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good Example: Rdio's remote control functionality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bad example: Zappos was using local cookies to store shipping cart data, so you couldn't continue the experience on another device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"Sync verbs, not just nouns"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h6 id="createaholisticexperience"&gt;Create a holistic experience&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inventory all elements and "cohesify" them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Store session data in the cloud, not locally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider using web views when developing your native app. &lt;em&gt;&amp;lt;-- Huh?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace "click" with "press." &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace "mobile" with anything else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Respect mental models.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="cameronspresentationhttpsspeakerdeckcomcameronmollcohesiveux2015"&gt;&lt;a href="https://speakerdeck.com/cameronmoll/cohesive-ux-2015"&gt;Cameron's presentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="rachelandrewdeploymentworkflow"&gt;Rachel Andrew: Deployment Workflow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/rachelandrew"&gt;@rachelandrew&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rachel's talk focused on Wordpress deployment. Check out her blog post on the topic for more details: &lt;a href="http://24ways.org/2014/developing-robust-deployment-procedures/"&gt;Developing Robust Deployment Procedures&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="keypoints"&gt;Key Points&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use a virtual machine&lt;/strong&gt; so your local environment is identical to the remote. You'll need
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/"&gt;VirtualBox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.vagrantup.com/"&gt;Vagrant&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://puphpet.com/"&gt;PuPHPet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add a deployment service&lt;/strong&gt; like &lt;a href="http://beanstalkapp.com/"&gt;Beanstalk&lt;/a&gt; to the git repo for your project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use a CDN&lt;/strong&gt; for the site's static assets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Still some unsolved problems:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Pre- and post-processed CSS and JS files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Backup management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Database migrations&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="jacobrossitheinputshouldntmatteradaptiveinputexperiences"&gt;Jacob Rossi: The Input Shouldn’t Matter (Adaptive Input Experiences)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jacobrossi"&gt;@jacobrossi&lt;/a&gt; – &lt;em&gt;Jacob works on Microsoft's Project Spartan, developing Microsoft Edge (the browser that is to replace IE).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="directmanipulation"&gt;Direct Manipulation&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Point and click” is so old fashioned. Make the user forget they’re touching glass. Touch has to work at 60fps so people feel like they’re interacting with the content, not the screen. Performance is key. If your gesture handling isn’t ongoing, then it isn’t direct manipulation. Gesture libraries aren’t great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to be natural. You can do a lot of stuff with gestures, but keep to the basics for the most part. Tap, swipe, pinch – keep it simple so the interaction is still intuitive and accessible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use native scrolling and zooming – it’s so important for performance. It’s not about moving down a document, it’s about keeping content stuck to a finger at 60fps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="scrolling"&gt;Scrolling&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New w3c standard called CSS Snap Points. Snap Points allow you to take a scrolling region and set up sticky points within the reason – so the browser knows where to snap-to content. Common use cases would be sliding carousels or sliding drawer menus. Can combine with CSS pointer events to do some really cool stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="zooming"&gt;Zooming&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Virtual Viewport &lt;br&gt;
Potential new CSS positioning standard – position:device-fixed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="pointerevents"&gt;Pointer Events&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to migrate away from mouse events. Pointer events abstract your code to be input agnostic. Simplicity of mouse events with support for multiple device types (even gestural devices like Leap), including multi-touch (even multi-user) events ,and device-specific properties like pressure. Pointer events can be device-independent when you want it; device-specific when you need it. Pointer events are in I.E., Edge. Firefox and Chrome. No word from Apple yet. JQuery is creating a polyfill for it though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Demo:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://github.com/jacobrossi/PointerPaint"&gt;https://github.com/jacobrossi/PointerPaint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pointer event properties:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;width&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;height&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pressure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tiltx&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tilty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The tilt properties could allow you to infer handedness – and possibly adjust the UI for left- vs. right-handed users.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="gestureevents"&gt;Gesture Events&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d have a gesture object that you can feed pointer events. Gesture-change events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gesture Event Properties&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;rotation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;translationX, translationY&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;velocityX, velocityY&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;velocityAngular&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;velocityExpansion &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="resources"&gt;Resources:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://w3.org/TR/pointerevents/"&gt;http://w3.org/TR/pointerevents/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://dev.w3.org/csswg/css-snappoints/"&gt;http://dev.w3.org/csswg/css-snappoints/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.webplatform.org/wiki/concepts/Pointer_Events"&gt;https://docs.webplatform.org/wiki/concepts/Pointer_Events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/jacobrossi"&gt;https://github.com/jacobrossi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="pattytolanddesignconsistencyfortheresponsiveweb"&gt;Patty Toland: Design Consistency for the Responsive Web&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pattytoland"&gt;@pattytoland&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The goal is to make a web that works for everyone.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are more far more likely to make a purchase if the site is designed for mobile. In fact, users will leave a site feeling negative if the site is NOT designed for mobile, and this negative feeling about the interaction translates directly into a negative feeling about the brand. It makes users feel like the company doesn’t care about their business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“One could describe design as a plan for arranging elements to accomplish a particular purpose.” &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;– Charles Eames&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to effective design is the ability of the designer to recognize as many constraints and possible and be willing to enthusiastically work within those constraints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design consistency isn’t about pixels – it’s about purpose.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at both the whole and the detail and make design decisions appropriate for the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s really hard to predict where your traffic is going to come from, and RWD needs to support a full spectrum of experiences, &lt;strong&gt;even the ones that haven’t been invented yet&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Great RWD is only achievable when there’s a really stable foundation in place.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="hierarchyforrwd"&gt;Hierarchy for RWD:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Style&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scale&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="speed"&gt;Speed&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People will choose a competitor when there is only a quarter of a second difference in performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More people access Facebook on 2G than 4G.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your analytics won’t tell you who left your site before it showed up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Factoring speed and performance is critical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filesize and page speed are design choices&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Challenges:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Images, video, audio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fonts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Third-party tools (ads, social media)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code frameworks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data networks&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always ask: Is it necessary? Is it necessary for everyone? Is it necessary for everyone immediately?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pare down to most essential and than optimize.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set performance goals in the design spec.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider perceived performance - render above the fold content first&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="access"&gt;Access&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There’s no good reason to limit access to your base content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Progressive enhancement is your friend.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;It ensures broad access and fault tolerance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s not all or nothing. Think differently about content, source order, structure, interaction.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Key access considerations:
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Core content (words, images)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Essential functionality (links, form elements)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enhance w/o blocking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessiblity and fallbacks&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Involve QA teams and note expected variations and approaches to testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://filamentgroup.com/lab"&gt;Filamentgroup.com/lab&lt;/a&gt; has tutorials for progressive enhancement and other things, with open source tools on github: &lt;a href="https://github.com/filamentgroup"&gt;github.com/filamentgroup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="scale"&gt;Scale&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Breakpoints
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For static designs 320, 480, 768, etc. are great. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Filament Group works with illustrator because it’s flexible! &lt;em&gt;&amp;lt;-- My kind of people!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We want simple math for templates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stacking, modular patterns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep template breakpoint logic simple&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus complexity in components
traditional design principles should guide your structural decisions. line lengths, etc. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;When the layout gets to a point that feels wrong, that’s when you set the breakpoint for the component. You don’t just have to change the width of the component, you can also consider changing font size, padding, etc.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider layering components that don’t fit on smaller screens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For tables, each column of table data has its own priority, and then that plays into breakpoints, where less important columns collapse down into collapsible panels. 
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/filamentgroup/tablesaw"&gt;TableSaw&lt;/a&gt; is an open source tool to handle this.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="style"&gt;Style&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scale to fit the content. Packaging design is an industry that does this really well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put style through the speed filter.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Are custom font weights worth it? How about rounded corners and gradients (js in IE8)? &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proceed with Caution:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Icon fonts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fixed positioning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Custom form elements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Animation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Internal scrolling&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Social widgets are really heavy. Load them async. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For approvals, QA, style guide reference: the code is the documentation. Pattern lab. Move to code as quickly as possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="takeaways"&gt;Takeaways:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Functional&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple grids/complex opponents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scale &amp;amp; style &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just enough design, code as documentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test real devices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h6 id="pattysslideshttpsdocsgooglecompresentationd1fh7bzne2leffuxi2cl6gaqdaynm3tv6_6d_mmsdokieedit"&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1Fh7bZne2lEffUxI2cL6gaqdayNm3tv6_6d_mmSdOkiE/edit"&gt;Patty’s Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="andybuddtheuxofuserexperience"&gt;Andy Budd: The UX of User Experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/andybudd"&gt;@andybudd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="cultofthewireframe"&gt;Cult of the Wireframe&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wireframes aren't the solution to every problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imagine if the aerospace industry used wireframes the way the web design industry does. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wireframes are lightweight tools to help designers think through a process and then share with the rest of the team. They aren't dogma. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People who wireframe – are they designers or documentation people?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="dunningkruegereffect"&gt;Dunning-Krueger Effect&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People who have a tiny bit of knowledge on a subject but really only know the tip of the iceberg. "Stupid is as stupid does." &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The reverse is imposter syndrome. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The D-K Effect is rampant in the design world, in part due to...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="dualityofthephraseux"&gt;Duality of the phrase UX:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defining the thing is hard. In different contexts, UX could mean any of the following: A job, a rule, a group, a field, the result of design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="theuxteam"&gt;The UX team:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Usability Specialist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information Architect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strategist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visual Designer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interaction Designer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="auserexperiencedesigneris"&gt;A user experience designer is:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"A conceptual designer who focuses on what a product or service does and how it behaves, rather than what it looks like."&lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;– Andy Budd&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h6 id="dansaffersmodel"&gt;Dan Saffer's Model:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/05/ux-diagram.jpg" alt="" title=""&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;Via: &lt;a href="http://www.kickerstudio.com/2008/12/the-disciplines-of-user-experience/"&gt;http://www.kickerstudio.com/2008/12/the-disciplines-of-user-experience/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="jasonmesutsmodel"&gt;Jason Mesut's Model:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interaction design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information architecture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/05/ux-diagram-2.jpg" alt=""&gt;
&lt;span class="caption"&gt;Via: &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/jasonmesut/sell-yourself-better-10"&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/jasonmesut/sell-yourself-better-10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="whatshapeofuxdesignerareyou"&gt;What shape of UX designer are you?&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tell potential employers and clients: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;  is what I do. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Y&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;  is what I don't do. How do I fit within your organization?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We're better as a team. It's better to have a group of good, but not stellar, designers rather than a rock star with an inflated ego and an attitude.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hiring focuses on the portfolio. Show sketches, pictures of you facilitating workshops, evidence of your problem solving skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The next desired skills? Prototyping and animation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="andrewclarkecreativityoverpredictability"&gt;Andrew Clarke: Creativity Over Predictability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://twitter.com/malarkey"&gt;@malarkey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"I look at today's web design with a growing sense of dissatisfaction. Designs lack energy and spontaneity. Nothing strays beyond the boundary of convention. We're in a soulless period."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&amp;quot;I fear design being crushed under the boot of UX.&amp;quot; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Malarkey"&gt;@Malarkey&lt;/a&gt; Agreed, but I fear creativity is crushed by budgets &amp;amp; profits. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/smashingconf?src=hash"&gt;#smashingconf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Richard Buecheler (@rb_design) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rb_design/status/593544098427981824"&gt;April 29, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/smashingconf-notes/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">891d7603-8a88-48af-b879-de8a09d71d76</guid><category>smashing</category><category>conf</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2015 22:04:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Second Month</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm two months in. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I’ve been feeling a bit scattered lately. Progress on the style guide project has been slow since I’ve been busy with travel and other projects. I’ve been starting too much and not finishing nearly enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a lighter note, I've really enjoyed exploring the Bay and spending time with my coworkers! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the things I’ve worked on in the last month:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="cirprojects"&gt;CIR Projects&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started designing an interactive for an upcoming &lt;a href="http://revealnews.org"&gt;Reveal&lt;/a&gt; story. (I wish I could say more about this.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continued development on a style guide for Reveal.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;I'm using &lt;a href="http://patternlab.io"&gt;Pattern Lab&lt;/a&gt;, which is pretty nice. I'm planning on writing a post about additional style guide resources soon.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="travel"&gt;Travel&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Took a short trip home. (Long-distance marriages are hard.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spent a week at SNDMakes &amp;amp; SNDDC.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;My post on the event: &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-second-month/../sndmakes-emojis-and-more/"&gt;SNDMakes: Emojis and more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My team's project: &lt;a href="http://sixfoot6.com/emojinius"&gt;EMOJINIUS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="relatedwork"&gt;Related Work&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepared a lightning talk for SNDMakes.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Check it out: &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-second-month/../sndmakes-a-lightning-talk/"&gt;Designing for Performance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Submitted session proposals for &lt;a href="http://srccon.org"&gt;SRCCON&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://nejsconf.com"&gt;NEJSConf&lt;/a&gt;. I had hoped to submit something for &lt;a href="http://ona15.journalists.org"&gt;ONA&lt;/a&gt; but wasn't organized enough. :(
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lo-fi Data Viz&lt;/strong&gt; (with &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/aboutaaron"&gt;@aboutaaron&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br&gt;Newsrooms developers often build applications and visualizations using dynamic tools like d3.js, AJAX, canvas and others. However, these approaches to data viz and digital storytelling often don't consider users who have low-bandwidth Internet connections, budget smartphones, screen readers or hi-res displays. This session will look at existing data visualization projects and see how they could be adapted to work on low-end phones, computers with accessibility enhancements and other environments. We'll also brainstorm techniques and approaches for building wonderful and beautiful digital stories that &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; can enjoy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rethinking the Mobile Data Viz Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;How can we improve the user experience of data-heavy interactives on mobile devices? What are the biggest problems we encounter, and where do we see opportunities for improvement? Let's look at examples of good small-screen visualizations – perhaps using native mobile apps for inspiration – and brainstorm how to apply similar design concepts to news apps for the mobile web.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SVG Animation with Snap.svg&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://snapsvg.io/"&gt;Snap.svg&lt;/a&gt; is a javascript library for creating and interacting with SVG in modern browsers. It’s pretty sweet and worth sharing with people. This session will walk through some basic demos, show people how to get started, and then share some inspiring “in the wild” examples of snap.svg in action.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tried to catch up on &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-second-month/../"&gt;blog posts&lt;/a&gt; RE: NICAR, SND, retrospectives...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="extracurricularprojects"&gt;Extracurricular Projects&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A former client of mine needed some updates to their website, so I spent a decent chunk of my evenings revisiting Wordpress for them.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/the-second-month/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">999200fc-907e-460b-8ef3-385788286bda</guid><category>opennews</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 23:44:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>#SNDMakes: Emojis and more</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I spent last week in Washington, D.C., at &lt;a href="http://www.snd.org/2015/04/60-participants-reimagine-photo-stories-during-sndmakes-at-snddc" target="_blank"&gt;#SNDMakes&lt;/a&gt;, a “boutique prototyping event” sponsored by the Society for News Design. I was lucky enough to be one of 60 designers, developers, and visual storytellers from newsrooms around the country who participated in the event. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My team designed &lt;a href="http://sixfoot6.com/emojinius/" target="_blank"&gt;EMOJINIUS&lt;/a&gt;, an emoji annotation system. We were exploring how we could add value to a story by making audience engagement easier and more visual – so we designed a Medium-style, in-line commenting solution that uses emoji instead of text comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Comments are often damaging rather than constructive. And sometimes you can say it better with an emoji. They’re fun and delightful — and have evolved into a legitimate visual language. There's an opportunity to lower the barrier for audience engagement, and create a safe experience for capturing and exposing even anonymous responses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a lot of fun working with &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/buttersdesign" target="_blank"&gt;Ellen&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/annemiaoli" target="_blank"&gt;Anne&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/sixfoot6" target="_blank"&gt;Ryan&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/oneillclaire" target="_blank"&gt;Claire&lt;/a&gt; on the project. Our team’s collective skillset was heavily slanted toward design and UX, so we spent a lot of time talking through scenarios and use cases, and less time developing a proof of concept. It was cool that the event had such a design focus – we didn't feel overly pressured to churn out a bunch of bad code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Emojithink with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/sixfoot6"&gt;@sixfoot6&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/ButtersDesign"&gt;@ButtersDesign&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/oneillclaire"&gt;@oneillclaire&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67"&gt;@julia67&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/sndmakes?src=hash"&gt;#sndmakes&lt;/a&gt; 🙅🙌 &lt;a href="http://t.co/B8DzsKh17h"&gt;pic.twitter.com/B8DzsKh17h&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Anne Li (@annemiaoli) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/annemiaoli/status/586602307158179842"&gt;April 10, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;After the #SNDMakes event wrapped up, I stuck around for the rest of the SNDDC workshop. I especially enjoyed &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hellbox" target="_blank"&gt;Martin McClellan's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.snd.org/dc2015/tiny-frames-mobile-first-design-inside-of-breaking-news/" target="_blank"&gt;session&lt;/a&gt; on the UX design process for the &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/BreakingNews" target="_blank"&gt;Breaking News&lt;/a&gt; mobile app. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was cool to see some examples of news-oriented product design. Working on mobile apps is a thing I'd like to do more of in the future, and it's always great to get a glimpse of another group's processes.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Martin McClellan &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hellbox"&gt;@hellbox&lt;/a&gt; goes behind the iterative design process on the &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/BreakingNews"&gt;@BreakingNews&lt;/a&gt; mobile app &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/SNDDC?src=hash"&gt;#SNDDC&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://t.co/QR6SXTy62Q"&gt;pic.twitter.com/QR6SXTy62Q&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dan Archer (@archcomix) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/archcomix/status/586940934157402112"&gt;April 11, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;Oh! I also gave a &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/sndmakes-emojis-and-more/../sndmakes-a-lightning-talk/"&gt;lightning talk&lt;/a&gt; during #SNDMakes on making performance-based design decisions. It was my first ever speaking engagement. I must say I was pretty intimidated to be speaking in front of such an amazing group, but I was pretty happy with how it turned out. The content was definitely the most technical (read: boring) of all the talks, but I still got a few laughs from the audience so I'll call it a win. 🎉&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/sndmakes-emojis-and-more/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a168eb87-7421-4c34-8e7b-c1085dbab810</guid><category>opennews</category><category>snd</category><category>conf</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 00:45:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>#SNDMakes: A Lightning Talk</title><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is my (essentially verbatim) lightning talk on Designing for Performance from &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23SNDMakes&amp;amp;src=tyah" target="_blank"&gt;#SNDMakes&lt;/a&gt; DC. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="designingforperformance"&gt;Designing for Performance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hi, I’m going to chat for a minute about Designing for Performance – or as I like to call it: &lt;strong&gt;Keeping People Happy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We like to talk a lot about building robust, delightful user experiences. After all, we’ve all spent the last day and a half reimagining visual storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We're trying to make picture stories more contextual and engaging – and that’s awesome! But what we frequently forget to note is that the easiest way to ruin an awesome interactive experience for your user comes from one pesky, underemphasized problem: &lt;strong&gt;Performance...or lack thereof&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m going to go over a list of problematic performance issues and supply some strategies to help keep people happy. These are pretty basic tips, but a quick refresher never hurt!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="problemarea1giganticimages"&gt;Problem Area 1: Gigantic Images&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we all know, images are the biggest hit to website performance. There's a couple things you can do to help combat the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, &lt;strong&gt;reevaluate the design&lt;/strong&gt; to see if you really need them. Sometimes they’re necessary; sometimes they’re not. And if you definitely need the whole full-screen immersive experience, &lt;strong&gt;make sure you optimize&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Size your images for both screen width and device type. If your set-up allows you to &lt;strong&gt;serve scaled images&lt;/strong&gt;, you should absolutely do so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consider image quality. Don’t serve images that are a billion times more dense than they need to be. &lt;a href="https://kraken.io/web-interface" taret="_blank"&gt;Kraken.io&lt;/a&gt; has a free web interface to &lt;strong&gt;losslessly compress images&lt;/strong&gt;. You should use it. It works a heck of a lot better than just saving for web in Photoshop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have a seriously image-heavy piece, &lt;strong&gt;preload your images&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And &lt;strong&gt;don’t forget about caching&lt;/strong&gt;. Don’t make people download unchanged files over and over again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="problemarea2fancypantsfonts"&gt;Problem Area 2: Fancy-pants Fonts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Web fonts are also big and heavy and slow down your page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number one thing is to &lt;strong&gt;keep the number of web fonts to a minimum&lt;/strong&gt;. This includes different font weights. Loads web fonts just aren’t necessary. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subset your font resources so you &lt;strong&gt;only deliver the glyphs you actually need&lt;/strong&gt; on a page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make sure your custom fonts are compressed&lt;/strong&gt; before you serve them. TrueType formats aren’t compressed by default, so you should GZIP those.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="problemarea3css"&gt;Problem Area 3: CSS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preprocessors are awesome&lt;/strong&gt;, but they can bloat your code pretty significantly, so be careful. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always &lt;strong&gt;minify&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember to &lt;strong&gt;avoid CSS properties that repaint the screen&lt;/strong&gt; on scroll. These include:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;CSS filters  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;overzealous box-shadows and transforms&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A note on responsive: &lt;strong&gt;The fewer media queries you need the better.&lt;/strong&gt; If your project can get away with a single-column layout, perfect.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="problemarea4js"&gt;Problem Area 4: JS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is a huge one that I’m not going to get into right now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But I will say this: &lt;strong&gt;Audit your dependencies.&lt;/strong&gt; Make sure you’re not including unnecessary code on the page – and try to ensure the rest of your code is as efficient as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="keytakeawayperformanceisafeature"&gt;Key Takeaway: Performance is a Feature&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that performance is a feature, and it has a huge impact on user experience. A fast site leads to happy users – let's &lt;strong&gt;keep people happy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;A handful of performance resources, for those interested. &lt;a href="https://t.co/DCizODACh3"&gt;https://t.co/DCizODACh3&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/SNDMakes?src=hash"&gt;#SNDMakes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Julia Smith (@julia67) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67/status/586242052960161792"&gt;April 9, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/sndmakes-a-lightning-talk/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">aad38c46-52eb-455f-885c-8f31ec9f5c55</guid><category>opennews</category><category>talks</category><category>snd</category><category>conf</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 18:01:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The First Month</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I've just wrapped up the first month (plus a week, because I'm slow) of my fellowship at the Center for Investigative Reporting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been grand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've been working on a variety of projects – some for the newsroom, some for my own research – and I am consuming a crazy amount of new information. I have a decent grasp on python now. I've collected a lot of great info about style guides and front-end best practices that I'm condensing into documentation for the team. I've been developing a component-driven framework to help build consistent user interfaces for &lt;a href="http://revealnews.org"&gt;Reveal&lt;/a&gt;'s interactive news apps. And I've been banging my head against a wall trying to figure out what I should focus on for conference session proposals. Woo!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also attended my first &lt;a href="http://ire.org/conferences/nicar2015/"&gt;NICAR&lt;/a&gt; and had – in all honesty – too good a time. It's been weeks now and I'm still having post-NICAR withdrawals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the most amazing thing about the fellowship so far has been witnessing the inner workings of an investigative news organization. I had very little exposure to the process behind data-driven journalism prior to the fellowship, so it's been eye-opening to see how everyone tracks down sources and data sets, cleans and verifies the data, and then turns their findings into awesome, compelling stories. I still haven't felt ready to pitch my own investigation, but thanks to the rest of the data team and some sessions at NICAR, I'm confident and excited to venture into that realm in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gotta get some bylines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And beyond the work produced at CIR, the amount of passion, talent, and skill my coworkers have is really inspiring. Everyone has so much expertise and puts so much energy into their projects. (I realize it sounds like this should be a given, but I've worked at a few places where it seemed like most people were essentially checked out. Not so at CIR, which is pretty cool.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I'm quite happy with my fellowship experience so far, and I'm excited to start sharing information at a more rapid pace. I've done a lot of pre-work (researching the brand and various best practices, completing a lot of tutorials, trying out different tools, helping out as needed) and I feel like I'm about to hit my stride on all the style guide work I've been doing. Plus I'm about to start work on my first data viz project, and I am super excited to get something out in the open. (Shout out to &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/aboutaaron"&gt;Aaron&lt;/a&gt; for bringing me onto the project.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good things are on the way.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/the-first-month/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a9718317-5212-4cf7-80a3-09ba15b4ba32</guid><category>opennews</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2015 21:36:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>#NICAR15: Underserved Topics</title><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is Part 2 of my thoughts on NICAR 2015. If you want to read about specific sessions, see &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/nicar15-part-2-the-analysis/../nicar/"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During NICAR, I took some mental notes of topics that I thought deserved additional attention from the “news nerd” community. I’m hoping to use this list to inspire sessions proposals for conferences through the rest of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="1accessibilityperformance"&gt;1) Accessibility &amp;amp; Performance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought many of the sessions could’ve put more emphasis (or could at least &lt;em&gt;mentioned&lt;/em&gt;) these two aspects of web development that are often ignored. I touched on this in my &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/nicar15-part-2-the-analysis/../nicar/"&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt;, and I’ll say it again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;News organizations, as entities dedicated to informing the public, need to be conscious of the implicit biases that come from inaccessible content. Ignoring accessibility limits the reach of your reporting and discriminates against a &lt;em&gt;not insignificant&lt;/em&gt; number of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accessibility and performance go hand-in-hand. Cool, flashy, dynamic elements are frequently also resource-heavy, slow, and inaccessible – but they don’t need to be that way. There are a bunch of relatively easy ways to make our interactives faster and more readable, and we need to incorporate these techniques into our development processes. Accessibility and performance shouldn’t be an afterthought, and I think it would be in the best interest of the community to talk about it more often. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="2mobilefriendlydataviz"&gt;2) Mobile-Friendly Data Viz&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another topic that seems to get pushed aside. I’ve heard a lot of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“It’s not possible to make good interactives on mobile.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“It’ll hurt our work on desktop.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“It’s not worth the effort.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“It’s too hard.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s bullshit. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, to make a news app work well on mobile requires &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; methodology than is commonly utilized today – but that doesn’t necessarily mean a &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; process or an inferior product. In fact, I’d argue that trying to make mobile-friendly interactives will significantly better serve your audience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote about this in my fellowship application last August:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need more engaging mobile news content – and a design pattern to present it. Online storytelling has made great strides, but the percentage of users who access content via their mobile device has increased significantly, and these newer forms of online storytelling aren’t keeping pace. Either performance on mobile is substandard, or the visual design and user experience is less than ideal. I’d like to work on a framework to better present and share data-driven content on the mobile web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have a great solution to this problem yet – but it's definitely worth discussing in detail during events like NICAR, SRCCON, MozFest, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="3nativemobileapps"&gt;3) Native Mobile Apps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard very little talk about native mobile apps for news. I haven’t thought about it much from my end either, but I am curious why this topic doesn’t get much traction. My assumption is that developing and maintaining native mobile apps could very quickly get expensive for news orgs, so I assume cost is the limiting factor. But does it have to be? Would it ever be worth producing small, single-purpose native apps? I’m thinking about news games and monetization. Curious.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/nicar15-part-2-the-analysis/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">d91cec66-a48e-414f-a435-9dc5ba507deb</guid><category>opennews</category><category>nicar</category><category>conf</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 23:05:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>#NICAR15: The Sessions</title><description>&lt;p&gt;NICAR 2015 was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked the way the conference was organized. I liked the variety and quality of sessions offered. And I really liked meeting all sorts of awesome people over those five days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;So &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/NICAR15?src=hash"&gt;#NICAR15&lt;/a&gt; is cool. Super fun meeting people I previously thought only existed on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Julia Smith (@julia67) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67/status/573383571592880128"&gt;March 5, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;  

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is simply a dump of notes from the sessions I attended. I'll give a brief overview of my thoughts on the conference as a whole (and a couple areas of opportunity that stood out to me) in a &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/nicar/../nicar15-part-2-the-analysis/"&gt;subsequent post&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="wednesday"&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941695target_blanktechraking10bootstrappingthenewsa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1695/" target="_blank"&gt;Techraking &amp;lt;=10: Bootstrapping the News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a pre-conference workshop presented by my lovely CIR coworkers. The goal was to get the participants' computers set up with a VM running Xubuntu 14.04, complete with all the goodies anyone might need for other hands-on sessions. After getting the machines set up, the class was mostly an introduction to the command line. My job was to help anyone who got stuck, which I thought was a little funny because I barely ever use the command line in my day-to-day experience. However, I quickly realized that my sporadic usage over the last couple years was plenty enough to help out with this training. So that felt good. And I was able to drop a little knowledge bomb regarding using nano to edit files: you can use &lt;code&gt;Ctrl + O&lt;/code&gt; to save a file without closing it. That'll save your work in progress, which is a small but mighty time-and-headache-saver. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/03/nano.jpg" alt="" title=""&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;The more you know.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="thursday"&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941700target_blankfromwordstopicturestextanalysisandvisualizationa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1700/" target="_blank"&gt;From words to pictures: Text analysis and visualization&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed this session and thought it was a good one to start with. It was an interesting look at visual presentations of text-based data – really good for inspiration. I left wondering how much of it would be useful on mobile devices. Will investigate. Here's the &lt;a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/283djj27aea1ut4/From-words-to-pictures_text-analysis-and-visualization_diakopoulos.pptx?dl=0"&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941701target_blanktheforgottenhistoryofdatajournalisma"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1701/" target="_blank"&gt;The forgotten history of data journalism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fun looking at all the firsts in data visualization. Much of the session covered this &lt;a href="http://www.propublica.org/nerds/item/antebellum-data-journalism-busted-abe-lincoln"&gt;report about Abraham Lincoln&lt;/a&gt;. I thought it would have been cool if the presentation went a little further, maybe into the early stages of computer-based visualisations, maybe something about Muriel Cooper...perhaps that's still too recent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941706target_blankuncoveringracialandeconomicdividesusingdataa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1706/" target="_blank"&gt;Uncovering racial and economic divides using data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This session was great, particularly Nikole Hannah-Jones' portion of it. She presented her &lt;a href="http://projects.propublica.org/segregation-now/"&gt;investigation&lt;/a&gt; of the resegregation that occurced after many states' desegregation orders expired. I'd like to see a project along the same lines specificaly for Omaha, which was released from a desegregation order in 1984 and is becoming more and more segregated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941714target_blankspacejournalismusingsatelliteimageryfordataprojectsa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1714/" target="_blank"&gt;Space journalism: Using satellite imagery for data projects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I missed Brian's session at MozFest, so I was really happy to see it at NICAR. Here's the info:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/briantjacobs/ae5510ca84ef172b2f5f?nicar" target="_blank"&gt;GitHub repo from speaker Brian Jacobs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://shaw.al.s3.amazonaws.com/nicar15/nicar-louisiana.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Presentation from speaker Al Shaw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/18281116/nicar-space.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Presentation from Brian T. Jacobs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941719target_blankhumanizingnumbersa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1719/" target="_blank"&gt;Humanizing numbers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a great session about the &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; behind visualizing data. Katie Parks' &lt;a href="http://www.katie-park.com/nicar-2015.pdf"&gt;projects&lt;/a&gt; were some of my favorites – they're great examples of alternative ways to display information. I particularly loved the concept behind the &lt;a href="http://hungerreport.org/missingdata/"&gt;2015 Hunger Report&lt;/a&gt; – how the interesting story is in the data that's &lt;em&gt;missing&lt;/em&gt; rather than the data that's available. The photo treatment in that story is pretty awesome too. Overall, I liked how this session focused on how to identify a human-centric story rather than how, technically, to create a graphic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="fellowshipmeetup"&gt;Fellowship Meetup&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2015 cohort met up to discuss our experiences so far. It's always nice to hear from everybody. Afterwards, we attended the Knight Foundation happy hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="friday"&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941732target_blankvisualjournalismfortinynewsdesksa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1732/" target="_blank"&gt;Visual journalism for tiny news desks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a session full of things to consider when working in a small newsroom. The audience had some good questions and feedback, including how to avoid performance issues with Google Sheets-powered graphics, and how to consider mobile when developing interactives on the cheap. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To avoid performance problems with Google Sheets, write a script to export a snapshot of the data from Google at a specified interval. Don't rely on the live feed from Google – because if your doc goes down, so does your graphic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quick ways to account for mobile are to 1) always provide data in an alternate format that's more accessible (like a table) and 2) export your graphics so the user doesn't have to run all the javascript to generate the graphic on the fly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941740target_blankjobsandcareerstraighttalkforandbyyoungunsa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1740/" target="_blank"&gt;Jobs and career straight-talk: For (and by) young'uns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very awkwardly got myself signed up to mentor j-students during this session. (Thanks, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jeremybmerrill"&gt;Jeremy Merrill&lt;/a&gt;, for being gracious!) I thought I might have a unique perspective, considering that I found my way to an awesome newsroom in a relatively unconventional way. Perhaps I'll elaborate on the things I hoped to share with journalism's youngins in another post. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the session ended up being more "Q&amp;amp;A with the panelists" and less "small group discussion with the mentors" than I was expecting, but it was still really interesting to hear what other mentors has to say about their own experiences getting to where they are today. At points the conversation devolved into a debate about whether or not grad school is necessary, and another debate about whether or not it was hard to find a job after graduating. In both those conversations, I thought the people who landed their dream job with ease, right out of undergrad, were a little insensitive to everyone else. I mean, I'm glad they're so talented that all the pieces fell into place for them, but that's pretty rare – so it'd be good to at least acknowledge that other people have had different experiences. And I don't mean that in a bitter way at all (I have been quite privileged myself), I'm just well aware that things don't always work out and opportunities aren't available to everyone equally, so it's not accurate or right to expect things to come as easily to others as they did to you. If that makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941750target_blankusingabstractiontogainknowledgefromnumbersa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1750/" target="_blank"&gt;Using abstraction to gain knowledge from numbers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probably the session where I absorbed the most. I had never heard data abstraction explained in such a concise way, which was awesome. Here are a couple quick takeaways, just for kicks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To show difference between two metrics: Consider plotting the difference itself instead of plotting two lines on a chart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To show long-term trends: Averages are good, smoothing is better, but plotting the change in trend over time is even better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a cycle plot to show long-term, cyclical data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To illustrate change in spatial data: Use a slope graph instead of a map&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.dropbox.com/s/6c6gkblukaou8li/NICAR_2015_tip_sheet.pdf?dl=0"&gt;Presentation from Robert Simmon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgconferencesnicar2015lightningtalkstarget_blanklightningtalksa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/conferences/nicar2015/lightning-talks/" target="_blank"&gt;Lightning Talks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the lightning talks, particularly the bit about the NYTimes' crazy-awesome dataviz tool, Mr. Chartmaker. They have done it. I worked on a similar project with a previous employer, and it was nowhere near as comprehensive or user friendly. Gives us all something to work towards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="saturday"&gt;Saturday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941756target_blankdesignvizwhattodoandwhatnottodoa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1756/" target="_blank"&gt;Design/Viz: What to do, and what not to do&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This session was pretty standard and had good advice, which you can read about &lt;a href="http://moiz.ca/talks/2015/nicar.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Q&amp;amp;A portion of the event, an audience member asked a question about accessibility and mobile performance, since most of the examples from the presentation were fairly heavy desktop-sized visualizations. The answer from one of the presenters was less than satisfactory: They don't worry accessibility for news applications because they don't think it's worth it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I disagree with that stance. Accessibility and mobile performance are becoming more and more important, especially as mobile audiences grow and &lt;a href="http://webaim.org/articles/laws/world/"&gt;global web accessibility legislation&lt;/a&gt; becomes more prominent. News organizations, as entities dedicated to informing the public, need to be conscious of the implicit biases that come from inaccessible content. Ignoring accessibility limits the reach of your reporting and discriminates against a &lt;em&gt;not insignificant&lt;/em&gt; number of people. I'm not arguing that people should avoid experimentation with modern techniques or large-scale projects – I just think it's increasingly important to provide alternative means to access information...I'll talk more about this later. Aaron Williams and I may submit a session proposal about this topic for &lt;a href="http://srccon.org/"&gt;SRCCON&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941759target_blanksensorjournalismbuzzorbsa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1759/" target="_blank"&gt;Sensor journalism: Buzz or BS?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fun session that was spoiled by an overtly sexist (and entirely avoidable) question during the Q&amp;amp;A.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941766target_blankmakingdatainformeddesigndecisionsa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1766/" target="_blank"&gt;Making data-informed design decisions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved this session. Using Google Analytics for multivariate testing is a thing I've been very interested in but have never had a chance to implement. Here are some key takeaways from the NPR's analysis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Users don’t need share buttons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a “care question” to help encourage users to take action after consuming a story.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Users are more likely to take action if presented with a yes or no question asking them how the story made them feel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For NPR, the care question made a huge difference in their conversion rates (significantly more users clicked on a button to donate to NPR)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1Lysx8Nr_lA3eDE1uQ7ZCiTDDiteGtV1b_DY9KQaHpMw/preview?sle=true&amp;amp;slide=id.p"&gt;PowerPoint from Tyler Fisher &amp;amp; Josh Kadis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a great read on the methodology behind NPR's multivariate testing, check out &lt;a href="http://blog.apps.npr.org/2015/02/26/multivariate-testing.html"&gt;this piece&lt;/a&gt;, cowritten by my fellow Fellow &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/livlab"&gt;Livia Labate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941678target_blankwebinspectorforcomplexscrapesa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1678/" target="_blank"&gt;Web Inspector for Complex Scrapes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time during this session, which was presented by the wonderful &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/esagara"&gt;Eric Sagara&lt;/a&gt;. It was all about how to reverse engineer awful ASP.NET and Flash-based web applications in order to scrape the data from them. This was a lot of fun for me because I've spent many years building awful .NET and Flash/Flex apps. It was super fun to approach it &lt;em&gt;from the other side&lt;/em&gt;. Plus there was a bit of a competition – who could find the data on a certain website first – and I was happy to remind the class that if you can't find any data in the HTTP requests, &lt;em&gt;look for it in the HTML source&lt;/em&gt;. It's probably embeded in a &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; block somewhere. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="womenofnicardinner"&gt;Women of NICAR Dinner&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was lovely. I didn't manage to talk to everyone I had hoped to – but Linda, Livia, Kavya, Tara and I had some great conversation! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sunday"&gt;Sunday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941785target_blankgameoflifedatafromdayonetothedayyoudiea"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1785/" target="_blank"&gt;Game of life: Data from day one to the day you die&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was somehow my first session about generating story ideas. It was fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941724target_blankdeepdivesa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1724/" target="_blank"&gt;Deep dives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at a few examples of data-driven news apps. Here's a &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/a/ire.org/document/d/17kdPo5qXz-HOn418vQQUaFinnaQI2sWgJ_wGLz0EvXg/edit" target="_blank"&gt;tipsheet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="ahrefhttpireorgeventsandtrainingevent14941787target_blankminingsearchabledatabasesforstoriesa"&gt;&lt;a href="http://ire.org/events-and-training/event/1494/1787/" target="_blank"&gt;Mining searchable databases for stories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought this sessions was really quite useful. I do wish it would've been a Thursday session though – it was a great introduction to what people actually mean when they say "computer-assisted reporting," which embarrassingly took me too long to really grasp. The session simply walked everyone through some go-to data sources, which are available on the tipsheet. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--For some of my overall thoughts on the conference, see [Part 2](../nicar15-part-2-the-analysis).--&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For notes from all the other sessions at NICAR, check out the &lt;a href="http://ire.org/conferences/nicar2015/tipsheets-and-links/" target="_blank"&gt;tipsheets and links&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/nicar/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">cb966cc8-b50b-498a-a796-b2600e2f39ee</guid><category>opennews</category><category>nicar</category><category>conf</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2015 23:04:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Cool fellowships at cool places</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Last August, I was sharing a bottle of wine with the amazing &lt;a href="http://jmac.creighton.edu/?page_id=234" target="_blank"&gt;Dr. Carol Zuegner&lt;/a&gt;, my friend and former j-school advisor, as we discussed how my newish job was going. I was working as a web developer for a &lt;a href="http://oxidedesign.com/" target="_blank"&gt;small graphic design studio&lt;/a&gt; and was feeling mostly content but somewhat underwhelmed with the work. And Carol, in all her wisdom, reminded me that I have “a very particular set of skills” …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/03/taken.jpg" alt="Liam Neeson in 'Taken'"&gt;
&lt;span class="caption"&gt;Not those kinds of skills.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…that news organizations are hungrily seeking. She asked if I'd considered applying for opportunities outside of Omaha – perhaps grad school, perhaps something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t put a ton of consideration into the suggestion – I was living quite the comfortable life in Omaha and was hesitant to disrupt it. I had also been working outside the news industry for the last three or four years and wasn't sure if my journalism degree was still relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, Carol sent me an email entitled “cool fellowships at cool places,” containing a link to the &lt;a href="http://opennews.org/what/fellowships/" target="_blank"&gt;Knight-Mozilla fellowship&lt;/a&gt; program. It was surprising how perfect it sounded. From a skills and interests perspective, it seemed like a tailor-made opportunity. And, incredibly, it included a reasonable stipend and time commitment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had two days to apply. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NBD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I drafted my responses to the application fairly quickly but spent most of those two days reading blog posts about the fellowship experience. Notable reading material included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://veltman.tumblr.com/post/94827905007/opennews-t-minus-36-hours" target="_blank"&gt;This one&lt;/a&gt; via &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/@veltman target=" _blank"=""&gt;@veltman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://veltman.tumblr.com/post/56132893301/code-the-newsroom-and-self-doubt" target="_blank"&gt;This one&lt;/a&gt; also via &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/@veltman target=" _blank"=""&gt;@veltman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://erikaowens.com/blog/who-should-apply-knight-mozilla-fellowship-you" target="_blank"&gt;This one&lt;/a&gt; via &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/@erika_owens" target="_blank"&gt;@erika_owens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://briantjacobs.com/john-cusack-on-becoming-a-2015-knight-mozilla-fellow/" target="_blank"&gt;This one&lt;/a&gt; via &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/@btjakes target=" _blank"=""&gt;@btjakes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided this was actually something I really really really wanted to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few hours before the deadline (not a record, BTW), I hit the submit button and hoped for the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The waiting game began. I cycled between ultra-confidence and crippling self-doubt on a near-daily basis as I anticipated a response from OpenNews. When I was feeling level-headed, I estimated I would make it into the group of semifinalists but probably not any further than that. When I made it past that point, I had no more expectations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two months leading up to the final fellowship decision felt like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/03/positivity-chart-1.jpg" alt="Chart: Positivity over Time"&gt;
&lt;span class="caption"&gt;I'm just trying to have fun here.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's a timeline of some tweet-sized feels:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="callout"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aug. 14&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Beginning to read about the fellowship. Very excited.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="callout"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aug. 16&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Application submitted. Feeling super confident because I thought my application materials turned out awesome.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="callout"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sept. 5&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Semifinalist notification. Happy but trying to stay realistic.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="callout"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sept. 10&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Prepping for first interview. Feeling confident; I usually interview pretty well.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="callout"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sept. 11&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Interviewed with OpenNews. Thought it went horribly. Had too much coffee and felt like I couldn’t keep my thoughts straight.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="callout"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sept. 19&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Finalist notification. Very pleasantly surprised. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="callout"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sept. 25&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Interview with CIR. Feeling pretty good about it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="callout"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oct. 1&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Still feeling good. Blind hope is balancing any lack of confidence. Should receive a final decision tomorrow.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="callout"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oct. 2&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;A day full of anxious excitement and anticipation. I am very jumpy.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="callout"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oct. 3&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Received news that a decision hasn’t been made yet. I'm convinced the fellowship was offered to another. Sad. Reevaluating all life decisions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="callout"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oct. 6&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Received another email. Still no news. At least this isn’t a rejection. I'm still in the running. Feeling slightly better.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="callout"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oct. 10&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Oh happy day! 2015 Knight-Mozilla fellow at the Center for Investigative Reporting. So excite!!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that's the brief overview of my experience with the fellowship selection process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One other thing to note – one reason my pre-semifinalist positivity remained high – is that I kept a close eye on the Google Analytics report for my personal website. I received very little traffic prior to applying for the fellowship, and visits to my site were almost entirely from Nebraska. After I applied, I started getting hits from other locations – New York, Chicago, D.C., London – places that definitely had a host news organization or other OpenNews presence. Occassionally, the ISP even said something super informative, like "National Public Radio." So I had a nice quantitative measure that my application likely made it past the first round of cuts, which took some of the edge off. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gotta love data.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/cool-fellowships-at-cool-places/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">19a22a94-044e-4ea8-a0d2-ae9de2293d21</guid><category>retrospective</category><category>opennews</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2015 06:15:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>