<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>musings</title><description>&lt;span class="tag"&gt;design&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="tag"&gt;code&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="tag"&gt;journalism&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="tag"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="tag"&gt;life&lt;/span&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/</link><generator>Ghost 0.5</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 19:32:45 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://julia67.github.io/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>#Audiohack: Timed data binding for HTML5 media with memento.js</title><description>&lt;p&gt;This American Life's &lt;a href="http://audiohackathon.com/"&gt;Audio Hackathon&lt;/a&gt; was last weekend. It was a good time exploring different ways to enhance podcast creation, discovery, and consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My team worked on a web app that synchronizes social and multimedia content – photos, ads, tweets, videos, maps, links, etc. – with an audio file. The basic idea was to make it easier for listeners to engage with external content referenced within a podcast episode. For example, if the host is talking about a specific celebrity tweet, this app could display said tweet at the specific time in the podcast when it's being referenced. It'd also be awesome for a show like &lt;a href="http://serialpodcast.org/"&gt;Serial&lt;/a&gt;, where the producers would be able to annotate the show with actual documents and additional details about the case – &lt;em&gt;synchronized show notes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the really valuable result of this hackathon project is the JavaScript tool that we (ahem, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/vijithassar"&gt;Vijith&lt;/a&gt;) wrote to handle time-based data binding for HTML5 media objects: &lt;a href="https://github.com/vijithassar/memento"&gt;memento.js&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the docs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Memento.js binds data to regions of audio or video and allows you to quickly recall the results at any point during playback or scrubbing. Calling the &lt;code&gt;.data()&lt;/code&gt; method on a memento object will retrieve the data corresponding to that point in time. Calling the &lt;code&gt;.data()&lt;/code&gt; method repeatedly at different points in time will retrieve different data.&lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;Conceptually, memento can be thought of as a way to slave all JavaScript execution to the playback as defined by the bound media node. It doesn't meaningfully use JavaScript events, though. Instead, it wraps around a playable media node and a queryable data structure, and then uses timing information from the former to deliver dynamic data payloads from the latter that automatically change over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/vijithassar/memento"&gt;Check it out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/audiohack-memento-js/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">23d7adce-f507-4842-8a60-cf1e4b85ffbc</guid><category>conf</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2015 19:02:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Seventh Month</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/10/BuenosAires-sm.jpg" alt="" title=""&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;The view from my hotel room in BA!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Month No. 7 included a trip to Buenos Aires, a workshop, a keynote, a hack week with my fellow fellows, some meetups, a wasted week due to a bad cold (ugh), and lots of planning for an exciting Month No. 8!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="events"&gt;Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="thefutureofjournalisminawikipediaworldbrhackshackersbayareameetup"&gt;The Future of Journalism in a Wikipedia World&lt;br&gt;Hacks/Hackers Bay Area Meetup&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.meetup.com/hacksandhackers/events/224478596/"&gt;This event&lt;/a&gt; brought together a panel of journalists, academics, and "superusers" to discuss the impact, possibilities, and partnership opportunities between Wikipedia and the news industry. Much of the discussion centered on issues related to fact-checking and the credibility of information on Wikipedia. Another hot discussion topic regarded encouraging journalists, as subject-matter experts, to contribute their reporting to Wikipedia articles. Interesting stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="hackshackersbuenosaires2015mediaparty"&gt;Hacks/Hackers Buenos Aires 2015 Media Party&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-seventh-month/../hhba-media-party-2015"&gt;Read about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="fellowshackweek"&gt;Fellows Hack Week!&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hack week was a lot of fun. Check out this &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-seventh-month/../hack-week-project"&gt;super fun tutorial&lt;/a&gt; I put together on animating matrix transformations on SVG elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="projects"&gt;Projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="publishedthelostthefound"&gt;Published: The Lost &amp;amp; The Found&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://lostandfound.revealnews.org/" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/10/Screen-Shot-2015-10-02-at-12-04-13-PM.png" alt="" title=""&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;&lt;a href="https://lostandfound.revealnews.org/" target="_blank"&gt;Check out the project on revealnews.org!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This investigation – a deep dive on U.S. missing and unidentified persons – has been in the works at CIR for years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"The Lost &amp;amp; The Found" web app has been in development in some form since March or so. It is an application that takes data from &lt;a href="http://www.namus.gov/"&gt;NAMUS.gov&lt;/a&gt; and repackages it into a simplified search interface so that users can more easily find potential matches among the missing and unidentified records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My involvement in the project was mostly as a technical advisor. Early in the reporting process, I helped data journalist Emmanuel Martinez write a Python scraper to pull information from the NAMUS site; for the final product, I advised our Google fellow, Allison McCartney, on best practices for front-end web development and debugging. Huge props to Allison, Emmanuel, and our fearless leader Michael Corey for all their work on this project!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="news"&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next month will be an extraordinarily busy one! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Audio Hackathon:&lt;/strong&gt; This American Life is putting on an a makers event to prototype new tools for podcasts. It's being held in Manhattan, and I'm super excited about it. I think there's a lot of room for innovation around audio on the web, and I'm looking forward to seeing what kinds of projects the teams come up with. I'm hoping to pitch a data sonification project, although that might be a stretch depending on the crowd. I'm also really happy that this event is in New York – I was hoping for a chance to get there during my fellowship.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ONA15:&lt;/strong&gt; The Online News Association's annual conference is at the end of September in Los Angeles. I haven't had a chance to attend in previous years, so I'm eager to see what it's all about. I think it'll provide good perspective and an opportunity to identify areas where tech for online journalism needs improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MIT Media Lab Open House:&lt;/strong&gt; I received a travel grant to go to the Media Lab's open house, so I'll be flying out to Boston immediately after ONA to check it out and connect with the Center for Civic Media. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code for America Summit:&lt;/strong&gt; And just in case I haven't tired of conferences after all that, I'll be attending the CFA Summit in Oakland at the beginning of October. I'm really interested in the overlap between the journalism and civic tech communities, and the speaker lineup for the event looks fabulous. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots to learn!&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/the-seventh-month/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">b95fbb83-424f-430d-91d8-6b40e3e31f6e</guid><category>opennews</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2015 19:32:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hack Week: More fun with SVG animation</title><description>&lt;p&gt;After the &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/hack-week-project/../hhba-media-party-2015/"&gt;HHBA Media Party&lt;/a&gt;, all of us Knight-Mozilla fellows stayed in a Buenos Aires for another week, working on side projects and exploring the city together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used my "hacking" time to continue working with &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//snapsvg.io/docs"&gt;Snap.svg&lt;/a&gt; – my hope was to complete a few more experiments that I could then incorporate into my workshop resources for &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;cad=rja&amp;amp;uact=8&amp;amp;ved=0CB0QFjAAahUKEwj84tPAn__HAhWLSZIKHY3gDl4&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2F2015.mozillafestival.org%2F&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNGo45gOnEhHvdxAEh8dn-LpSTpygw&amp;amp;bvm=bv.102829193,d.aWw"&gt;MozFest&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One experiment was particularly fun to work on: an animated map of travel destinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/09/travel-map.gif" alt="" title=""&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;Please enjoy this massive GIF; I don't have a real demo up anywhere yet.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn't have enough time to finish it – and the animation is quite unrefined at the moment – but it's still sorta fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes a list of events (with dates and location information), plots them on a map, and animates the travel to-and-from the destination. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how exactly does it move a star from one location to the next? &lt;em&gt;I'm so glad you asked.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="howtomakeansvgstarshootsomewhere"&gt;How to make an SVG star shoot somewhere&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This example will illustrate how to create and move a single star. I removed all sequencing functionality for simplicity's sake, so we're just going to look at how to make a star shape fly to New York City from San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you're interested in the whole thing, check out the &lt;a href="https://github.com/julia67/travel-map"&gt;project on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. Heads up, though – I'm passively working on it, so it'll be in various states of completion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="step0defineyourdata"&gt;Step 0: Define your data&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need two data files – one that contains individual event data and looks like something like this: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var data = [
  {
    "event": "Audio Hackathon",
    "location": "New York City",
    "startDate": "09-19-2015",
    "endDate": "09-20-2015",
    "from": "San Francisco",
    "to": "Los Angeles"
  }
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and another that contains coordinates for different locations, like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var locations = [
  {
    "location": "Los Angeles",
    "x": 140,
    "y": 132
  },      
  {
    "location": "New York City",
    "x": 244,
    "y": 114
  },
  {
    "location": "San Francisco",
    "x": 135,
    "y": 120
  }
]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coordinates themselves are fairly arbitrary for this exercise – they're simply the XY coordinates for each city's location on the &lt;a href="https://github.com/julia67/travel-map/raw/master/media/BlankMap-World6.svg"&gt;SVG file&lt;/a&gt; we're using (they're not actual geocoordinates).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="step1getsomelocationinformation"&gt;Step 1: Get some location information&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see in the events list, each event object includes a field for the primary destination (&lt;code&gt;"location": "New York City"&lt;/code&gt;) as well as the cities we left  (&lt;code&gt;"from": "San Francisco"&lt;/code&gt;) and return to (&lt;code&gt;"to": "Los Angeles"&lt;/code&gt;). So the first thing we want to do is get the coordinates of each of these cities from the locations data (&lt;code&gt;var locations&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var startX, startY, destX, destY, endX, endY;

for (var i=0; i&amp;lt;locations.length; i++){

  // look for the entry with a matching starting `location` value
  if (locations[i].location == data[0].from){
    startX = locations[i].x;
    startY = locations[i].y;
  }

  // look for the entry with a matching destination `location` value
  if (locations[i].location == data[0].location){
    destX = locations[i].x;
    destY = locations[i].y;
  }

  // look for the entry with a matching ending `location` value
  if (locations[i].location == data[0].to){
    endX = locations[i].x;
    endY = locations[i].y;
  }

}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h6 id="step2createaprettystarshape"&gt;Step 2: Create a pretty star shape&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made a star in Illustrator, saved it as an SVG, and copied the path data into my JS code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var star = g.path('M 0.000 15.000,L 23.511 32.361,L 14.266 4.635,L 38.042 -12.361,L 8.817 -12.135,L 0.000 -40.000,L -8.817 -12.135,L -38.042 -12.361,L -14.266 4.635,L -23.511 32.361,L 0.000 15.000');
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h6 id="step3definethestarsstartposition"&gt;Step 3: Define the star's start position&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//snapsvg.io/docs"&gt;Snap.svg&lt;/a&gt;, all transformations are represented by a matrix object, which is a collection of parameters that describe the transformation you want to perform on an element. The matrix object can than be further manipulated via methods like &lt;code&gt;clone()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;invert()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;rotate()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;scale()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;translate()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var startMatrix = new Snap.Matrix();

startMatrix.translate(startX, startY);
startMatrix.scale(.15, .15);

star.attr({
  transform: startMatrix,
  class: 'event',
  fill: '#00a99d'
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we created a new matrix and then passed the starting X and Y positions to the &lt;code&gt;translate&lt;/code&gt; method. We used the &lt;code&gt;scale&lt;/code&gt; method to make the star shape a reasonable size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the matrix was defined, we declared it as an attribute to the star element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="step4definethedestinationandendpositions"&gt;Step 4: Define the destination and end positions&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var destMatrix = new Snap.Matrix(),
    endMatrix = new Snap.Matrix();

destMatrix.translate(destX, destY);
destMatrix.scale(.15, .15);

endMatrix.translate(endX, endY);
endMatrix.scale(.15, .15);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we defined the Snap matrices for the destination XY coordinates and the end XY coordinates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="step5animatethematrixtransforms"&gt;Step 5: Animate the matrix transforms&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snap's animation method is pretty straightforward: you pass it the attributes you want to change, the duration of the animation, the type of easing you want, and then a callback function that fires when the animation is complete. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;// move star to the destination position
star.animate({
  transform: destMatrix
}, 1000, mina.easeinout, function(){

  setTimeout(function(){
    // move star to the end position
    star.animate({
      transform: endMatrix
    }, 1000, mina.easeinout);
  }, 500); //time between arriving and leaving destination

});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the first animation transforms the star from its starting position to its destination position. Once the first animation is complete, we trigger the final animation in the callback function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/09/one-star.gif" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="fin"&gt;Fin&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you have it: a tiny star that starts in one position, flies somewhere else, and ends in a third spot. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src="http://julia67.github.io//giphy.com/embed/R6bDgXEXCLcIw" width="480" height="360" frameborder="0" class="giphy-embed" style="max-width:100%" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/hack-week-project/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">47475805-0b6c-474b-ac30-6603f355d7ae</guid><category>opennews</category><category>tutorial</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2015 00:11:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>#HHBA Media Party</title><description>&lt;p&gt;¡Hola de Buenos Aires! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hacks/Hackers BA &lt;a href="http://mediaparty.info/"&gt;Media Party&lt;/a&gt; was held last week at the &lt;a href="http://www.ciudadculturalkonex.org/"&gt;Ciudad Cultural Konex&lt;/a&gt; in Buenos Aires, Argentina. It was a super cool event and reminded me, again, that I need to learn how to speak Spanish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://goo.gl/photos/wNSKRijpJkVFPgrEA" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/09/hhba.jpg" alt="" title=""&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;Photos by Mitch Barry.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few of the fellows gave keynote talks and facilitated workshops – I did both. The keynotes were in the mornings during the single-track portion of the conference, and the multi-track workshops were held during the afternoons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="keynoteanimatingdataslideshttpjuliasmithcomhhbakeynote"&gt;Keynote: Animating Data (&lt;a href="http://julia-smith.com/hhba-keynote/"&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This goal of this talk was to illustrate how animation can enhance data visualization and then show examples from different news organizations that have used animation really successfully in their projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;.&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67"&gt;@julia67&lt;/a&gt; presenting on power of animating data to tell stories. (hey, losing ground! &lt;a href="http://t.co/DoR23n7txa"&gt;http://t.co/DoR23n7txa&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/hhba?src=hash"&gt;#hhba&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://t.co/dtrn3dk4tQ"&gt;pic.twitter.com/dtrn3dk4tQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Amanda Zamora (@amzam) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/amzam/status/637274066664210432"&gt;August 28, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I thought it went pretty well. I was much more comfortable on stage this time (compared to NEJSConf), and I was excited to have another opportunity to demo my &lt;a href="http://julia-smith.com/animated-data-sonification/"&gt;Mass Shootings&lt;/a&gt; project. It's been interesting to see people's reactions to it. Some seem to really like it and think it's a moving and tasteful way to represent the gravity of the data. Other people interpret the audio in an entirely different way than I intended – it seems they perceive the piano track as sounding "happy." I may write more on this later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Creating an emotional response animating &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/dataviz?src=hash"&gt;#dataviz&lt;/a&gt; Here: US mass shootings &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67"&gt;@julia67&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MediaParty?src=hash"&gt;#MediaParty&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/hhba?src=hash"&gt;#hhba&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://t.co/hHxMve3UXW"&gt;pic.twitter.com/hHxMve3UXW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Maria Cruz (@marianarra_) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/marianarra_/status/637274392393871360"&gt;August 28, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Fantastic animated and sonified &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/dataviz?src=hash"&gt;#dataviz&lt;/a&gt; showing mass shootings in the U.S. by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67"&gt;@julia67&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://t.co/aWIo8XeMPd"&gt;http://t.co/aWIo8XeMPd&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/hhba?src=hash"&gt;#hhba&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Zara Rahman (@zararah) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zararah/status/637274803230130176"&gt;August 28, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h4 id="workshopanimationwithsnapsvgtutorialhttpsgithubcomjulia67snapbasicsslideshttpjuliasmithcomnejsconf"&gt;Workshop: Animation with Snap.svg (&lt;a href="https://github.com/julia67/snap-basics"&gt;Tutorial&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf"&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading the workshop was a lot of fun. I did a quick run through my slides to review the "whys" of SVG and animation, and then we jumped into the hands-on portion of the event. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking everyone through my &lt;a href="https://github.com/julia67/snap-basics"&gt;tutorial repo&lt;/a&gt; went pretty smoothly. It ended up being a bit short, so I'll definitely add more to it before &lt;a href="https://2015.mozillafestival.org/"&gt;MozFest&lt;/a&gt;. But even though I ran out of planned examples, a handful of participants were really engaged with questions and ideas, so we ended up going through additional examples on the fly, which was great and filled up the full two hours. I'm excited to give the workshop another go at MozFest in November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Thanks for your workshop of Animation with Snap &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67"&gt;@julia67&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Enzo Oliva (@enzoliva) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/enzoliva/status/638436705352163328"&gt;August 31, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h4 id="enoughaboutme"&gt;Enough about me&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the conference was awesome. &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/blejman"&gt;Mariano Blejman&lt;/a&gt; and team did a fabulous job organizing and coordinating the main event and all the dinners and afterparties. It was super cool seeing my fellow fellows onstage talking about &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/frnsys"&gt;building online communities&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/kavyasukumar"&gt;why you don't need to learn computer science&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/jjelosua"&gt;iterative learning through elections&lt;/a&gt;. The other talks were really interesting too. I especially enjoyed &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/JenniferBrandel"&gt;Jennifer Brandel&lt;/a&gt;'s talk about &lt;a href="http://www.wearehearken.com/"&gt;Hearken&lt;/a&gt;, "an audience-driven platform enabling newsrooms to engage the public throughout the reporting process." Really insightful stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus it's so exciting to be in Argentina! This has been my first time in South America, and I am loving it. The food – carne! chorizo! dulce de leche! – is amazing. And my favorite thing thusfar has been the Media Party's closing event, which was held at La Catedral Tango Club. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/09/tango.jpg" alt="" title=""&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;Dancing people are pretty.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Media Party ended on Saturday, but the 2015 fellows are sticking around Argentina for the next couple days to code things and spend some quality time together. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good times.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/hhba-media-party-2015/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">359d124b-18a0-4a4a-a0e6-72bdef71de24</guid><category>opennews</category><category>conf</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2015 19:42:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Sixth Month</title><description>&lt;p&gt;The Sixth Month is over already? For real??&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's baffling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've had a bit of a breakthrough in the last four weeks. I wrote a &lt;a href="https://source.opennews.org/en-US/articles/building-data-viz-all/"&gt;Source post&lt;/a&gt;, gave a &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-sixth-month/../nejsconf-snap-svg"&gt;solo talk&lt;/a&gt; to a 200+ person audience, and finally &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//julia-smith.com/animated-data-sonification"&gt;made something cool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; – so I'm feeling pretty productive and gaining some confidence when it comes to sharing the stuff I've been working on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've also been applying for a handful of things – grants, hack events, etc. – because I've started to realize that this fellowship isn't going to last forever (&lt;em&gt;sadness&lt;/em&gt;) and I need to make the most of the remaining four months and figure out what to do after it's over. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think grad school is up next for me, but that leaves a six-month gap that I need to fill with either freelance work or possibly a grant-funded project. We'll see. &lt;em&gt;If anyone knows of some short-term opportunities, please &lt;a href="mailto:julia@julia-smith.com"&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, here's what I've been up to in the last month:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="events"&gt;Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="portlandcodeconvening"&gt;Portland Code Convening&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-sixth-month/../portland-cc-now-on-source/"&gt;Read all about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="nebraskajavascriptconferencenejsconf"&gt;Nebraska JavaScript Conference (#NEJSConf)&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/08/zleatherman-nejsconf.jpg" alt=""&gt;
&lt;span class="caption"&gt;Photo by &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/zachleat/status/629861052327530497"&gt;Zach Leatherman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was invited to speak at the first-annual &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//nejsconf.com/"&gt;NEJS Conf&lt;/a&gt;, which was held in Omaha on Aug. 7. The conference was much larger than I expected when I initially submitted my session proposal – turns out it was a single-track event with more than 200 attendees and some first-rate keynotes including &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/beep"&gt;Ethan Marcotte&lt;/a&gt; (AKA &lt;em&gt;the guy who single-handedly started the responsive web design movement&lt;/em&gt;). I may have been a little intimidated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also the first time I had ever been invited to a "speakers dinner" – and this one happened to involve a limousine and steaks. Totally unnecessary. Still pretty awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event itself was great; everything went off without a hitch. It was held at the Omaha Zoo, so during breaks between speakers they brought in animals, including this adorable little guy named Garbanzo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/08/garbanzo.jpg" alt=""&gt;
&lt;span class="caption"&gt;Garbanzo the Green Acouchi. So cute. Photo by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/davereid/status/629756515407106048"&gt;Dave Reid&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was not in the best headspace before giving my talk, but it turned out OK. I walked through &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//julia-smith.com/nejsconf"&gt;these slides&lt;/a&gt; and then gave a demo of my &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//julia-smith.com/animated-data-sonification"&gt;mass shootings&lt;/a&gt; piece...which really took down the mood (&lt;em&gt;whoops&lt;/em&gt;) but was impressively effective at eliciting an emotional response from the audience.  I was excited about that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, Ethan said some really nice things and totally made my day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/czlDCwi4VzY?start=179" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nejsconf"&gt;@nejsconf&lt;/a&gt;:&amp;#10;&amp;#10;I have done basically nothing with dataviz, but &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67"&gt;@julia67&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nejsconf?src=hash"&gt;#nejsconf&lt;/a&gt; talk already has me wanting to check out Snap.svg.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ethan Marcotte (@beep) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/beep/status/629738100168654848"&gt;August 7, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/nejsconf"&gt;@nejsconf&lt;/a&gt;:&amp;#10;&amp;#10;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67"&gt;@julia67&lt;/a&gt;’s animated, audio-enhanced timeline of mass shooting fatalities. Wow. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nejsconf?src=hash"&gt;#nejsconf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ethan Marcotte (@beep) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/beep/status/629740976387436548"&gt;August 7, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;...I'm only a little star-struck. Ha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also really awesome talking to a bunch of folks about the &lt;a href="https://opennews.org/what/fellowships/"&gt;Knight-Mozilla fellowship&lt;/a&gt; after the event. I hope some of them were conviced to apply! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="projects"&gt;Projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="inprogressanimateddatasonification"&gt;In Progress: Animated Data Sonification&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//julia-smith.com/animated-data-sonification"&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/08/mass-shootings.jpg" alt="" title=""&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;An interpretation of &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-sixth-month/www.motherjones.com/politics/2012/12/mass-shootings-mother-jones-full-data"&gt;Mother Jones' data&lt;/a&gt; on mass shootings in the United States since 1982.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check it out:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//julia-smith.com/animated-data-sonification"&gt;Demo&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/julia67/animated-data-sonification"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am really happy with how this project is turning out. It's a totally custom visualiztion. It's minimal. It's emotive. It works well. And it gave me a reason to experiment with three things that had been on my bucket list for awhile: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/cirlabs/miditime/"&gt;MIDITime&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//snapsvg.io"&gt;Snap.svg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTML5 audio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still need to clean up the code and make some usability enhancements. I'd also love to make a mobile-specific (vertical) layout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erin Kissane asked me to write a &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//source.opennews.org/"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; post on it – so be on the lookout for that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="presentationanimationbasicswithsnapsvg"&gt;Presentation: Animation Basics with Snap.svg&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//julia-smith.com/nejsconf"&gt;the Slides&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="inprogressdatavizforalldvfacomponents"&gt;In Progress: Data Viz for All &amp;amp; DVfA Components&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/julia67/data-viz-for-all"&gt;DVfA&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/julia67/dvfa-components"&gt;DVfA Components&lt;/a&gt; on GitHub. You can also read about the project on Source: &lt;a href="https://source.opennews.org/en-US/articles/building-data-viz-all/"&gt;Building on Data Viz for All&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="news"&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Massively cool stuff coming up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hacks/Hackers Buenos Aires Media Party 2015:&lt;/strong&gt; I'll be presenting on SVG animation and DVfA.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fellows Hack Week:&lt;/strong&gt; Working from Argentina!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/the-sixth-month/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">363142ac-ba37-4509-a6bb-355554eed241</guid><category>opennews</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2015 21:10:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>#NEJSConf: Animation basics with Snap.svg</title><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is my talk on SVG animation from &lt;a href="https://nejsconf.com/2015/julia67/"&gt;#NEJSConf&lt;/a&gt; in Omaha. You can walk through the &lt;a href="http://julia.nightbirdstudios.com/nejsconf/"&gt;presentation slides here&lt;/a&gt;. (They're also  &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/julia67/snap"&gt;on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="whysvg"&gt;Why SVG&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we’re going to talk about SVG. More specifically, we're going to talk about how to animate SVG graphics with a really awesome little library called &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/nejsconf-snap-svg/"&gt;Snap&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how many of you work with SVG regularly, but just in case you’re unfamiliar, here’s a quick refresher on why SVG is a totally viable thing to use in your web apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SVG stands for Scalable Vector Graphic, and it is exactly that. It’s a 2-d, vector-based image format, and it opens up a lot of possibilities for interesting interaction design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="resolutionindependent"&gt;Resolution Independent&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first useful thing about SVG is that it’s resolution independent. It looks good at any size and will never appear fuzzy. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;iframe src="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#why-svg-1" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="450" frameborder="0" style="border:1px solid #ccc;margin-bottom:0;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#why-svg-1"&gt;Full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="lightweight"&gt;Lightweight&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the images are defined as text elements and attributes, SVG images can be significantly smaller to download than you standard JPGs, PNGs or GIFs, and that opens a lot of doors for creating visually complex yet performant experiences for your users. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;iframe src="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#why-svg-2" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="450" frameborder="0" style="border:1px solid #ccc;margin-bottom:0;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#why-svg-2"&gt;Full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, if you need the same image in different sizes (like a logo or icons), you’re in luck! With SVG you can use the same file for all purposes, which cuts down on bandwidth. Along the same lines, you can repurpose the same image file with different colors and treatments, which negates the need for raster sprites with all the possible hover states and retina sizes, etc. You don’t need to do that anymore and it’s wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="styleable"&gt;Styleable&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I just mentioned, SVGs are styleable. You can access and modify different properties for paths, shapes, gradients, opacity, filters, text, clipping masks – all those good things. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;iframe src="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#why-svg-3" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="450" frameborder="0" style="border:1px solid #ccc;margin-bottom:0;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#why-svg-3"&gt;Full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="interactive"&gt;Interactive&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can attach event handlers to SVG elements with JavaScript, similar to the way you’re used to with HTML. Plus, SVG is based on a coordinate system so it’s easy to animate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#why-svg-4" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="450" frameborder="0" style="border:1px solid #ccc;margin-bottom:0;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#why-svg-4"&gt;Full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, be aware that jQuery selectors and SVGs don't mix. How this plays out in practice is that if you’re trying to use jQuery to work with an SVG, you'll end up writing a lot more vanilla JavaScript than you probably bargained for. So don’t use jQuery with SVG. Just use Snap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="accessibility"&gt;Accessibility&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SVG is rendered to the page as markup, so all the text within the graphic is available to search engines and – as long as you configure it appropriately – it’s also available to assistive technologies like screen readers. Plus with the SVG 2.0 spec that’s coming out, we’ll have more universal support for tabindexes on SVG elements. I’m super excited about this because it opens all sorts of doors for exposing data via keyboard navigation. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;iframe src="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#why-svg-5" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="450" frameborder="0" style="border:1px solid #ccc;margin-bottom:0;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#why-svg-5"&gt;Full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="whyanimate"&gt;Why animate?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now that we know why we’re using SVG, the next question is: Why make the effort to animate things?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a question I’ve struggled with, having very conflicted opinions about when the extra code and computation for animations does or does not outweigh performance concerns. There’s a give-and-take with that decision-making process, but for now, I’d like to put performance hits on the backburner and just focus on the opportunities that animation offers to enhance the user experience. We'll go over the goals of animating on-screen elements, and then review a few best practices for animated interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="itsabouttime"&gt;It's about time&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you think about animations in interaction design, the key thing to keep in mind is that animations are time-based – and &lt;strong&gt;good animations smooth the transition of an element’s state in order to add meaning and value to the user's experience&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things like physics, speed, and synchronization all come into play when designing animations. The more you can mimic true-to-life experiences, the more seamless and invisible the animation will be to your user – which is exactly what you want. The goal of animating an element is to make the screen function more like the real world. In real life, things don’t abruptly change state. An ice cube doesn’t go from solid to liquid in a split second. Rather, it melts, transitioning from one state to the next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the transition an ice cube and a puddle of water seem like two completely different things – it’s the transition that ties them together. And the same goes for animated graphics and UI elements. When things change abruptly, your user gets lost. But by animating the change – for example, animating the scroll to an anchor link instead of directly jumping to it – then your user always knows how they came to be where they are, and context is preserved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a basic example: &lt;br&gt;
&lt;iframe src="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#why-animate-1" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="450" frameborder="0" style="border:1px solid #ccc;margin-bottom:0;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#why-animate-1"&gt;Full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook’s Jake Blakely recently wrote an awesome post on &lt;a href="http://jake.ly/journal/animations.html"&gt;the “why” of animation design&lt;/a&gt;, some of which we’ve gone over already, but I’ll summarize again here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Animations create more fluid transitions, which feels more natural to the user.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Animations can provide visual feedback or context to an interaction. An example would be a progress bar or loading icon – something to let the user know that an action is happening.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Animations can guide the user’s attentions. Our eyes are naturally drawn to motion, and animations can help the user know what to do next. An example is a submit button that changes color once the form is complete, which catches the user’s attention and lets them know which action to take next.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Animations can elicit an emotional response. This is the really interesting thing about effective animations – because animations that are well executed – animations that seem fluid and natural and mimic the real world in some way – have real-world effects on humans. Humans can be delighted or disappointed or frustrated, all thanks to your UI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id="whysnapsvg"&gt;Why Snap.svg?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we know why we should use SVG and why we should animate things, the next question is: Why Snap? Why should we use Snap.svg to animate our vector graphics?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quick answer is: &lt;strong&gt;because it’s super easy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course there’s a longer answer. Here’s some background on Snap: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="snapreplacesraphael"&gt;Snap replaces Raphael&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snap is essentially the replacement for Raphael.js,  the original go-to library for SVG animation. Raphael was really cool because it could support browsers as far back as IE6 with it’s VML fallback for environments that didn’t support SVG. Thankfully, most of us don’t need to support old IE anymore, so we can stop weighing down our apps with huge libraries that try to cater to every old IE quirk. Snap.svg supports IE9+, and it was written by the same guy, Dmitri Baranovskiy, who created Raphael back in the day. So it’s a very comprehensive solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="snapispowerful"&gt;Snap is powerful&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The functionality goes far beyond what Raphael was able to do. Snap allows you to not only generate new SVGs, but it will actually work with existing SVGs that you created in Illustrator or Inkscape or some other way. It provides a robust API for manipulating SVG content, and the animations it supports are spectacular – smooth, performant, and they even work surprisingly well on mobile devices. The official Snap.svg website describes the animation API as “simple and intuitive” – but it actually is. A click is a click, a hover’s a hover, and &lt;code&gt;.animate()&lt;/code&gt; gets you into all sorts of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="snapisfreeandopensource"&gt;Snap is free and open source&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also fairly lightweight. What's not to love?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="howcanyougetstarted"&gt;How can you get started?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some slides:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#snippet-1" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="450" frameborder="0" style="border:1px solid #ccc;margin-bottom:0;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#snippet-1"&gt;Full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#snippet-2" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="450" frameborder="0" style="border:1px solid #ccc;margin-bottom:0;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#snippet-2"&gt;Full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#snippet-3" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="450" frameborder="0" style="border:1px solid #ccc;margin-bottom:0;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#snippet-3"&gt;Full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#snippet-4" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="450" frameborder="0" style="border:1px solid #ccc;margin-bottom:0;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#snippet-4"&gt;Full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#snippet-5" scrolling="no" width="100%" height="450" frameborder="0" style="border:1px solid #ccc;margin-bottom:0;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia-smith.com/nejsconf/#snippet-5"&gt;Full screen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="resources"&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;  
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://moxieusa.com/Blog/2015/March/Top%2010%20Reasons%20Why%20SVG%20Is%20the%20New%20Flash.aspx"&gt;Why SVG is awesome&lt;/a&gt; | Andy Makely&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://jake.ly/journal/animations.html"&gt;Animation best practices&lt;/a&gt; | Jake Blakely&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.google.com/design/spec/animation/authentic-motion.html"&gt;Authentic motion&lt;/a&gt; | Google&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://sarasoueidan.com/demos/interactive-svg-coordinate-system/index.html"&gt;Interactive SVG Coordinate System&lt;/a&gt; | Sara Soueidan&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://svg.dabbles.info/"&gt;SVG Dabbles&lt;/a&gt; | @ianscoding&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/nejsconf-snap-svg/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">15ce5e80-49e5-4557-97ab-a63777319226</guid><category>talks</category><category>conf</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 20:45:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Code Convening: Now on Source</title><description>&lt;p&gt;The 2015 Fellows met up in Portland, Oregon at the end of July to work on some of our open-source projects. We each brought a colleague from our host newsrooms and had a fabulous time coding things and trying as many Portland brews as possible in a three-day timespan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/08/codeconvening.jpg" alt="" title=""&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;Photo by &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/livlab/status/624744909782650880"&gt;Livia Labate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My project, again, was &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/julia67/data-viz-for-all"&gt;Data Viz for All&lt;/a&gt; – the guidelines for accessible and mobile-friendly interactives that I started tackling a few months ago. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//source.opennews.org"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt; published &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//source.opennews.org/en-US/articles/building-data-viz-all/"&gt;my write-up&lt;/a&gt; of the work Eric Sagara and I did during the code convening. &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//source.opennews.org/en-US/articles/building-data-viz-all/"&gt;Read it here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goal was to start building out a &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/julia67/dvfa-components"&gt;library of UI components&lt;/a&gt; that we could use as examples within the official DVfA documentation. After that, we plan to reuse those components as the basis for a &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//revealnews.org"&gt;Reveal&lt;/a&gt; news application styleguide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Read more about the project on &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//source.opennews.org/en-US/articles/building-data-viz-all/"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/portland-cc-now-on-source/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">e3637845-a80a-4e11-9b3b-8482560edfbe</guid><category>opennews</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Aug 2015 04:02:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Welcome, fellow news nerds</title><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://opennews.org/what/fellowships/"&gt;Knight-Mozilla fellowship&lt;/a&gt; is super awesome. If you've ever wanted to work in a newsroom, build cool things, and travel a lot – &lt;a href="https://opennews.org/what/fellowships/apply/"&gt;you should apply&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm more than halfway through my fellowship now, and it’s neat to look back at all the things I’ve been able to do: I've worked on news apps, spoken at conferences, learned tons of new skills, participated in hackathons, traveled a bit… It’s been a fantastic experience so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://livialabate.com/says/so-you-think-you-can-dance/"&gt;Livia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://spaceandtim.es/opennews/fellowship_status"&gt;Francis&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://blog.kavyasukumar.com/paging-developers-to-newsrooms/"&gt;Kavya&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.juanelosua.com/posts/fellowship/fellowship-midpoint/"&gt;Juan&lt;/a&gt; already shared their notes on life as a fellow, and I’ve been keeping track of my fellowship with monthly checkins: &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/one-of-us/../the-first-month/"&gt;The First Month&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/one-of-us/../the-second-month/"&gt;The Second Month&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/one-of-us/../the-third-month/"&gt;The Third Month&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/one-of-us/../the-fourth-month/"&gt;The Fourth Month&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/one-of-us/../the-fifth-month/"&gt;The Fifth Month&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's just one other thing I'd like to add. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, &lt;strong&gt;the most enjoyable, valuable aspect of the fellowship is simply the exposure to the rest of the journalism-developer community&lt;/strong&gt; – the "news nerds," as they're sometimes called. These are folks who care deeply about journalism and technology, and there's a lot of crossover with other areas like open source, data science, design, civic tech, etc. This community is active and welcoming. Coming from the outside, it was surprising how immediately I identified with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn't involved with OpenNews or the broader network before the fellowship started; in fact, I was barely aware it existed. I was very settled in Omaha – my hometown, which is notably &lt;em&gt;not coastal&lt;/em&gt; – and although I was designing things, working with data, and writing code every day for work, I had never contributed to a real open source project. I had participated in a single civic hackathon, and it had been years since I had freelanced as a print designer for the local newspaper. &lt;strong&gt;I was dancing around the edge of news nerdery&lt;/strong&gt;, but hadn't had the full introduction or the right opportunity to dive in. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/one-of-us/../cool-fellowships-at-cool-places/"&gt;I learned about the fellowship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But enough with the backstory. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is: &lt;strong&gt;The &lt;a href="https://opennews.org/what/fellowships/"&gt;Knight-Mozilla fellowship&lt;/a&gt; introduced me to this vibrant, friendly, and intellectually engaging group of people.&lt;/strong&gt; Working in a major newsroom gives you the opportunity to connect with your coworkers – who are connected to their colleagues at various global organizations – and suddenly you're in an extended network of people who all care about journalism and tech. You also become part of a growing group of Knight-Mozilla alumni, which is a network in itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the fellowship provides opportunities to interact with the extended community remotely via the &lt;a href="https://opennews.org/what/community/calls/"&gt;OpenNews community calls&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="https://www.ire.org/resource-center/listservs/subscribe-nicar-l/"&gt;NICAR listserv&lt;/a&gt;, and Twitter. It also provides the means to meet and collaborate in-person at &lt;a href="https://opennews.org/what/community/convenings/"&gt;code convenings&lt;/a&gt;, meetups, hack days, and conferences &lt;em&gt;around the world&lt;/em&gt;. (Frequent travel is another fun new thing for me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/08/badges.jpg" alt="" title=""&gt;&lt;span class="caption"&gt;And that's just five months' worth.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And meeting people at conferences is especially great because it's super easy to stay in touch with everyone afterwards – the expanded network is invaluable. It's awesome that you can travel to a city where you previously didn't know anyone, and now you can reach out to a new connection and either meet up or get suggestions for places to visit. And I realize this is an obvious sequence of events for many – but I &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp; would've been comfortable doing that prior to this fellowship, and that speaks to the &lt;strong&gt;level of accessibility this community offers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You know what's even better? &lt;strong&gt;We're here for you, too.&lt;/strong&gt; Follow people &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/julia67"&gt;on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. Join a &lt;a href="https://opennews.org/what/community/calls/"&gt;community call&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://opennews.org/what/fellowships/apply/"&gt;Apply for a fellowship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. If you're even tangentially interested in journalism and the open web, you're a news nerd already. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is for you. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Still need some convincing?&lt;/strong&gt; Read &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/veltman"&gt;Noah Veltman's&lt;/a&gt; 2013 post on imposter syndrome: &lt;a href="http://veltman.tumblr.com/post/56132893301/code-the-newsroom-and-self-doubt"&gt;Code, the newsroom, and self-doubt&lt;/a&gt;. It did the trick for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/one-of-us/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">728beaa3-3e35-41a8-a33c-043223c7fbf6</guid><category>opennews</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 04 Aug 2015 08:44:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Fifth Month</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve hit the halfway point. My sentiments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I've started a lot of projects but haven't finished nearly as many. I think that's OK as long as there's still progress.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The lack of formal project management processes in the newsroom is starting to affect my enthusiasm, so I'm hoping to pivot and put more focus on developing tools and documentation rather than editorial pieces. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It just hit me that I have &lt;em&gt;no idea&lt;/em&gt; what I’ll be doing after the fellowship, so that's something for me to start thinking about!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I was up to during the last month:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="events"&gt;Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="srccon"&gt;SRCCON&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SRCCON was a great conference. OpenNews puts so much &lt;a href="https://opennews.org/blog/srccon-human-stuff/"&gt;thought and care&lt;/a&gt; into making the event a good experience for all participants, and it definitely didn't go unnoticed. The pacing was perfect, dietary options were considerate, and they provided a variety of activities that fell outside the standard afterparty, which was nice. Personally, I especially appreciated the "quiet workspace" on Thursday, which allowed me to prepare for my session on Friday without locking myself in my hotel room! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sessions I attended were great, too, of course. &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-fifth-month/../srccon-inspiration/"&gt;I wrote about a few of them&lt;/a&gt; previously.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="projects"&gt;Projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="publishedarevolvingdoorinthenuclearweaponsindustry"&gt;Published: A revolving door in the nuclear weapons industry&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-fifth-month/../the-third-month/#supersecretprojectno1"&gt;Super-Secret Project No. 1&lt;/a&gt; from previous posts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.revealnews.org/article/a-revolving-door-in-the-nuclear-weapons-industry/" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/07/revolving-door.jpg" alt="" title=""&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check it out:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.revealnews.org/article/a-revolving-door-in-the-nuclear-weapons-industry/"&gt;Interactive Graphic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project strengths:&lt;/strong&gt; It's mobile-friendly (lightweight and designed for small screens) and keyboard accessible. It also passes all the checkpoints on my &lt;a href="https://github.com/julia67/data-viz-for-all/tree/master/Pre-Production%20Checklist"&gt;Data Viz for All: Pre-Production Checklist&lt;/a&gt; – so hurray for practicing what I preach!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opportunities for improvement:&lt;/strong&gt; From a technical standpoint, I'm satisfied with the way this project turned out. I also wrote a separate post about some of the &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-fifth-month/../no-surprises-please/"&gt;ways we can improve our development, testing, and deployment processes&lt;/a&gt; – it's worth a read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="inprogresssupersecretprojectsforreveal"&gt;In progress: Super-Secret Projects for Reveal&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project No. 4:&lt;/strong&gt; It's about the drought. I'm helping a data reporter with SVG and UI stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project No. 5:&lt;/strong&gt; This is a big project for &lt;a href="https://revealnews.org"&gt;Reveal&lt;/a&gt;. I'm minimally involved – mostly helping out with JavaScript.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="onholdaccessiblesvggenerator"&gt;On-hold: Accessible SVG Generator&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have much opportunity to work on this project this month, sadly. Hopefully I can pick it up again in The Seventh Month because The Sixth Month is already booked!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="news"&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's a couple cool things coming up in the next four weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portland Code Convening:&lt;/strong&gt; The fellows (each with a colleague from the newsroom) will be spending a couple days in Portland working on some open source projects. Should be a good time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;#NEJSConf:&lt;/strong&gt; I'll be speaking about SVG animation at &lt;a href="https://nejsconf.com/"&gt;NEJS Conf: Javascript in the wild&lt;/a&gt;. I'm pretty excited about it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/the-fifth-month/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">deb3b065-da74-492d-86ce-dd1255b905cb</guid><category>opennews</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2015 19:06:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>No surprises please</title><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is a retrospective on a painful project launch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, CIR published a &lt;a href="https://www.revealnews.org/article/new-mexico-thrives-on-nuclear-bomb-despite-us-pledge-to-reduce-arsenal/"&gt;big investigation on the nuclear weapons industry&lt;/a&gt;. The report includes three interactive graphics: two slippy maps and a timeline of sorts. The launch was far from perfect – I wrote a 2,000-word internal report on everything that went wrong and how to avoid similar issues next time – and I wanted to riff on some those topics here as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But first, a little background information. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without getting too specific, the main problem with the launch was that the graphics didn't display on initial page load. The underlying cause was that the SSL implementation on revealnews.org prevented &lt;a href="https://github.com/nprapps/pym.js"&gt;Pym&lt;/a&gt; from loading, and differences between our testing and production environments prevented anyone from noticing the issue before the article went live. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not good. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, no one at CIR has authorization to fix issues with the server because the website is managed by an outside firm. As such, we couldn't resolve the real problem and had to resort to hotfixes. For two of the graphics, I could simply swap out Pym for static iframes, which wasn't a huge deal. On the other hand, my &lt;a href="https://www.revealnews.org/article/a-revolving-door-in-the-nuclear-weapons-industry/"&gt;Revolving Door&lt;/a&gt; graphic was very vertically variable – and it relied heavily on Pym. I had to actually rewrite all the code to make it work directly in Wordpress' text editor, which is ugly as hell and horrific from a maintainability perspective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, not good. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I got the hotfixes in place fairly quickly and no one died. &lt;em&gt;But the fun doesn't stop there.&lt;/em&gt; We also identified a handful of smaller bugs with the slippy maps post-launch that can be traced back to two main issues with our development and editorial processes (the real topic of this post):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Incomplete Requirements Gathering  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insufficient QA Testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id="1incompleterequirementsgathering"&gt;1. Incomplete Requirements Gathering&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slippy map graphics were both designed to be full-screen desktop applications. They were built as stand-alone applications and had lots of features that come along with stand-alone apps – like internal scrolling, anchor links, full window width and height, a vertical sidebar area, and external linkage. They were very obviously supposed to function &lt;em&gt;on their own&lt;/em&gt; rather than embedded in an article page. (They were also never optimized for mobile, but that's another story.) And yet, where can you find these apps? Embedded in an article. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This illustrates a fundamental misunderstanding of requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm sure the graphics would've been designed differently if it had been clear from the beginning that the intent was to publish the graphics inside the story instead of as a supporting stand-alone app. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, here's a list of things to clarify with your editors &lt;em&gt;at the beginning&lt;/em&gt; of a project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What's the objective for this graphic?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Mark all that apply. If more than one, please specify priority.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provide additional information that &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt; in the report&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Display information from the report in an alternative way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide a tool for the public to use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make something "fun" or "delightful"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get clicks on social media&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where will the graphic run?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Mark all that apply. If more than one, please specify priority.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Embedded in an article on our main website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In its own page on our main website&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As an entirely separate app, not on the main site&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embedded in an article on partner websites&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When is the story running?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;Please choose one.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;This week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next month&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other, please specify &amp;#95;&amp;#95;&amp;#95;&amp;#95;&amp;#95;&amp;#95;&amp;#95;&amp;#95;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answering questions like these will help ensure everyone is on the same page from the beginning. This allows the news apps folks to produce the right kind of product, and it helps set editors' expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="2insufficientqatesting"&gt;2. Insufficient QA Testing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stemming from the requirements problem comes insufficient QA testing. In the case of this nukes project, almost all of the editing and testing happened while the graphics were still in their stand-alone form. They had been cycling through the editorial process since April. The marching order to embed the graphics in an article page didn't happen until July. By then, all involved were experiencing testing burnout, we lost our slippy map developer (He's busy being awesome at &lt;a href="http://www.sfchronicle.com/"&gt;The Chronicle&lt;/a&gt; now!), and details were overlooked. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, no one at the organization had identified the discrepancies between the preview and production environments for revealnews.org – so when we &lt;em&gt;were&lt;/em&gt; testing, we weren't testing the right things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The obvious solution is, firstly, to identify the appropriate testing procedures to more closely replicate our production environment. And secondly, it would be helpful to hold off on significant review of graphics until they are in the correct format, presented in exactly the same way they will be published. That could help save everyone from burning out too early and overlooking obvious bugs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="inconclusion"&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt like these graphics were handled with too editorial a focus. There were no official requirements, no set design process, no project checkpoints, no meetings, no defined testing strategy, no integration process. But at the end of the day, we were dealing with code and we should have approached it as such. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We need to approach the creation of our interactive graphics as technology products with legitimate development processes in place.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way we can document different procedures (like how to test things appropriately) and define workflows for design, development, testing, and deployment. We can make sure the right people are included and consulted at the right times in the process, and we can identify and resolve pain points earlier and more comprehensively. We can present our best work without delay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now that there's attention on the issue, we can take steps to improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fun aside! Today also birthed the best and worst backhanded compliment I've ever received:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Yours is less sophisticated, but it looks far better on mobile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/no-surprises-please/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">9b328356-ebae-4ebb-a3d3-8e3521d09540</guid><category>retrospective</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 01:48:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>#SRCCON: Feeling inspired</title><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//srccon.org"&gt;SRCCON&lt;/a&gt; was last week, and it was awesome. Good discussion. Good coffee. Good times. I've come to really enjoy these news nerd "reunions" of sorts – it's fun to see everyone I don't get to work with on a daily basis and put faces to names of people from the OpenNews community calls and Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the sessions I went to were definitely engaging, although I was a little surprised by the lack of technical knowledge-sharing. I think the most concrete thing I learned was how to play "Magic the Gathering" – not that that was a problem!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, the shortage of technical discussion was far outweighed by the incredible amount of brainstorming that happened around various industry issues. I wanted to take a little time to comment on a few of these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="digitalworkflowprocesses"&gt;Digital Workflow Processes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/MaryJoWebster"&gt;MaryJo Webster&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/cjsinner"&gt;C.J. Sinner&lt;/a&gt; led an awesome and quite necessary – even overdue? – session called "Let’s Create an Ideal Digital Workflow." Session participants broke into groups and discussed one of my most favorite things in the whole world: project management. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the truth. Yes, I am a dork.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Project management is so, so important for technical projects – and yes, technical projects &lt;em&gt;in journalism&lt;/em&gt; are still technical projects, and editorial processes should be adapted accordingly. (TBH, the lack of true project management is the main thing that's been driving me crazy during my fellowship. I realize now that I was quite spoiled in previous jobs where I worked with some extremely talented PMs – on teams that had concrete processes in place.) I think there's a lot of opportunity for newsrooms to adopt some basic project management practices from other industries that would significantly improve our digital workflows. I'll go into detail at another time – but at the moment, I'll leave you with the process we discussed during the session itself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Document project objectives  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify roles and responsibilities (&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Responsibility_assignment_matrix"&gt;RASCI&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kickoff: Establish project management/communication tools and set deadlines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build prototype&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iterate with user testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Launch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discuss lessons learned&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this the &lt;em&gt;exact&lt;/em&gt; workflow I'd champion? Nope. It's missing a few key pieces (like design and QA, for example) but it's a decent start. I'd love to see more discussions on this topic. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;This digital workflow session is fabulous. Project management makes me so happy. Thanks &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/MaryJoWebster"&gt;@MaryJoWebster&lt;/a&gt; for facilitating. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/srccon?src=hash"&gt;#srccon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Julia Smith (@julia67) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67/status/614201794671947776"&gt;June 25, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(If you're interested in seeing the other workflows from the SRCCON session, &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1S6ms4pAMSlNpl8icrTtsHpxOpNldYWQkXQOSSwEd5UM/edit?pli=1&amp;amp;overridemobile=true"&gt;read the official session notes&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="ethicsofuxdinjournalism"&gt;Ethics of UXD in Journalism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fellow fellow &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/livlab"&gt;Livia Labate&lt;/a&gt;, along with &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/JoeGermuska"&gt;Joe Germuska&lt;/a&gt;, facilitated an awesome discussion about maintaining journalistic integrity while designing user experiences for news products (stories, websites, apps, interactives, etc.). &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1r9L0pAknMVub0MX82-KYnk71k3ZPiei_9dO6yEBPKZc/edit"&gt;Read the transcript&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The session, "Journalistic Objectivity and User-Centered Design," posed the following question: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There used to be a concept of objective truth, and news saw its job as presenting it to people. If you are focusing on users, does that still work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prompt generated more questions from the participants:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where does objectivity meet with transparency?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where does the conflict happen?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What stories are worth telling?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where is the divide between UI and content? &lt;em&gt;Is there a divide?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of this boiled down to the idea that developing a news platform or product may not necessarily be journalistic by nature and falls in a different category than creating news content, which &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; inherently journalistic and should abide by classical ideals including objectivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vocal opponent to this idea was ProPublica's &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/kleinmatic"&gt;Scott Klein&lt;/a&gt;, who said, "I disagree strongly with the notion that there is a separation between these concerns in newsroom – that there is a thing called 'actual journalism' and then something else that is a 'product.' I think it’s the wrong framing. We’re all journalists doing this work. You have the responsibilities that journalists have."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe a difference exists between the UI and the content, but I don't think this difference excuses product designers from journalistic responsibility. An example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Color.&lt;/strong&gt; Color has meaning (green = good, red = bad, etc.), so the colors in an interface shouldn't compromise the objectivity of the product's content. 
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acceptable design decision:&lt;/strong&gt; User research shows that people will click a blue button over any other color – so you choose to use the color blue to indicate action items within your interface. These action items include things like "read more" buttons and sortable table headers and don't affect the meaning of the article or data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problematic design decision:&lt;/strong&gt; If you, as a designer, are working on a graphic and decide to use a red color scale because you want to imply that something is subjectively bad, you're editorializing the data and using design to influence the user in a problematic way. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My stance: &lt;strong&gt;Design isn't inherently journalistic &lt;em&gt;until it becomes so&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; As such, UI/UX/product designers need to use their powers for good.  This is true for news website design, but it's especially true for things like news apps and interactive graphics. The designer's focus should be on creating the best user experience (guide people to click the right things, find the important information, get where they're trying to go), but in doing so, designers need to be conscious of their choices and make every effort to avoid design decisions that would affect the objectivity of the editorial content contained within their product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="mobileembraceit"&gt;Mobile: Embrace it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/aboutaaron"&gt;Aaron Williams&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/zhoyoyo"&gt;Youyou Zhou&lt;/a&gt; and I facilitated a session on improving interactives and data visualizations for mobile devices. I provided some resources &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/julia67/data-viz-for-all/"&gt;on Github&lt;/a&gt;, and participants updated &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//etherpad.mozilla.org/srccon2015-mobile-dataviz"&gt;this etherpad&lt;/a&gt; with ideas from their small-group discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I was pretty happy with how the session turned out, but I do have one major topic I'd like to discuss further: &lt;strong&gt;Building graphics for mobile doesn't have to be hellish.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, much of the session's commentary about designing for mobile was negative, as illustrated in tweets like this one, which received a disheartening amount of attention: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&amp;quot;One of the solutions we have for doing interactives on mobile is: don&amp;#39;t.&amp;quot; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/srccon?src=hash"&gt;#srccon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Heather Billings (@hbillings) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hbillings/status/614537795365941248"&gt;June 26, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;That's a pretty standard reaction. And, sure, ensuring interactives work well on mobile is complex and is too often an afterthought – &lt;em&gt;but it doesn't need to be this way&lt;/em&gt;. That's why we wanted to do this session: to get people thinking about mobile and provide them with &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/julia67/data-viz-for-all/"&gt;resources&lt;/a&gt; (examples, design patterns, code snippets, and inspiration) to make building mobile interactives easier and more effective. And we, the news nerd community, need to do a better job building open-source tools and frameworks with mobile in mind. "Mobile-first" may be a good philosophy to adopt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my part, I will continue to update the &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/julia67/data-viz-for-all/"&gt;Data Viz for All&lt;/a&gt; repo – and I invite others to contribute!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;going to refer back to this all the time: &lt;a href="https://t.co/7Limy51E5l"&gt;https://t.co/7Limy51E5l&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#10;&amp;#10;thanks &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/aboutaaron"&gt;@aboutaaron&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julia67"&gt;@julia67&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/zhoyoyo"&gt;@zhoyoyo&lt;/a&gt;! &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/srccon?src=hash"&gt;#srccon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Priya Krishnakumar (@priyakkumar) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/priyakkumar/status/614546634291200002"&gt;June 26, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  

&lt;script async src="http://julia67.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/srccon-inspiration/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">ab76dcaf-89a9-4d9c-a25c-46386001c835</guid><category>opennews</category><category>conf</category><category>srccon</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2015 04:48:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tinkering with Twitter's API</title><description>&lt;p&gt;OpenNews brought all of us Knight-Mozilla fellows to Minneapolis a day early for a low-key, pre-SRCCON hack day. The theme of the event was "Quant Selfish," so the goal was to make something out of personal data related to whichever topic seemed interesting. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/kavyasukumar"&gt;Kavya&lt;/a&gt; and I thought it might be fun to play with the Twitter API. The idea was to get a list of unrequited Twitter friendships – the accounts you follow that never returned the favor. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Drumroll, please...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inspired by all those Twitterfolk who don't follow you back...now...without further ado...we present to you:&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//kavyasukumar.com/apps/yunofollow/follow.html"&gt;YUNOFOLLOW&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;and &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//github.com/julia67/yuno"&gt;its undocumented GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;...and the crowd goes wild!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/07/yuno.jpg" alt=""&gt;
&lt;span class="caption"&gt;Here we have all 383 of my (that's &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/julia67"&gt;@julia67&lt;/a&gt;'s) unrequited friendships.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this isn't anything special or ground-breaking in the least – I had never worked with the Twitter API before, so I figured I should document the steps that went into making this Twitter app.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="makingaclientsideappwithtwitterdata"&gt;Making a client-side app with Twitter data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kavya and I only wanted to work on the front end for this, so we used &lt;a href="https://oauth.io/"&gt;oauth.io&lt;/a&gt; for OAuth integration and user management. The trickiest part was configuring the authentication piece; working with the Twitter API itself was pretty straight-forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="step1createthetwitterapplication"&gt;Step 1: Create the Twitter Application&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//apps.twitter.com"&gt;apps.twitter.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//apps.twitter.com/app/new"&gt;Create New App&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill in the application details. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Put &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://oauth.io/auth"&gt;https://oauth.io/auth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; as the callback URL.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make note of the &lt;strong&gt;Consumer Key&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Consumer Secret&lt;/strong&gt; under the &lt;strong&gt;Keys and Access Tokens&lt;/strong&gt; tab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id="step2configureoauthio"&gt;Step 2: Configure OAuth.io&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://oauth.io/"&gt;oauth.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://oauth.io/signup"&gt;Sign up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://oauth.io/signin"&gt;Sign in&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;Create an app&lt;/strong&gt;. This will generate the &lt;strong&gt;App Keys&lt;/strong&gt; (the Public Key and Private Key necessary to initialize the SDK). Find them under the &lt;strong&gt;General&lt;/strong&gt; screen.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the domain where you will host the app to the &lt;strong&gt;Domains &amp;amp; URLs whitelist&lt;/strong&gt; box on the &lt;strong&gt;General&lt;/strong&gt; screen.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;Integrated APIs&lt;/strong&gt; in the sidebar. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Click the &lt;strong&gt;Add API&lt;/strong&gt; button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose &lt;strong&gt;Twitter&lt;/strong&gt; from the available options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the Twitter &lt;strong&gt;Consumer Key&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Secret Key&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;from Step 1.4&lt;/em&gt; to the &lt;strong&gt;client_id&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;client_secret&lt;/strong&gt; fields. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;strong&gt;Try Auth&lt;/strong&gt;. If all goes well, you'll receive a success message containing the code you'll need to initialize OAuth from your app.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;OAuth.initialize('YOUR OAUTH.IO PUBLIC KEY GOES HERE');  
OAuth.popup('twitter').done(function(result) {  
    console.log(result);
    // do some stuff with result
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h4 id="step3writesomecode"&gt;Step 3: Write some code&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Include the oauth.io script on the page. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script src="scripts/dist/oauth.js"&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initialize OAuth. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;code&gt;OAuth.initialize('YOUR OAUTH.IO PUBLIC KEY GOES HERE');&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//docs.oauth.io/#authorize-with-a-popup"&gt;Authorize the app&lt;/a&gt; and save the result to a javascript object that will make HTTP calls to the Twitter API.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var provider = 'twitter';  
OAuth.popup(provider)  
.done(function(result) { // OAuth worked as expected
    twitterObj= result; 
    twitterObj.me()
    .done(function (response) { // Twitter user exists
        console.log('You're on Twitter!');
        console.log('Name: ', response.name);
        console.log(response.raw);
    })
    .fail(function (err) { // Twitter user wasn't found
        console.log(err); 
    });
})
.fail(function (err) { // OAuth didn't work
    console.log(err); 
});

$('button').click(function(){
    var friendsURL = 'https://api.twitter.com/1.1/friends/ids.json';
    twitterObj.get(friendsURL).done(function(data) {
        friendsIDs = data.ids;
    }).fail(function(err) {
        console.log(err);
    });
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's about it. We've identified a handful of issues with our code (which we wrote rather hastily) – but as this was just for fun, we're probably not going to fix anything. The goal was to identify our unrequited friendships – and identify them we did! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you're interested in trying something like this, definitely check out the &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//docs.oauth.io/"&gt;oauth.io docs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://dev.twitter.com/rest/public"&gt;Twitter API docs&lt;/a&gt;. Also, &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/hyper_linda"&gt;Linda&lt;/a&gt; found a &lt;a href="https://github.com/sferik/t"&gt;cool command line tool&lt;/a&gt; that does essentially the same thing – it's pretty spiffy if you're into that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/tinkering-with-twitters-api/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">a79e63fd-6207-4ceb-b140-eea4ddc091e8</guid><category>opennews</category><category>tutorial</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2015 07:04:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Fourth Month</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Month No. 4 was busy...and pretty decent overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a few graphics published on &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//revealnews.org"&gt;revealnews.org&lt;/a&gt;. I attended a couple great conferences. I mentored some people. Another one of my session proposals was accepted. &lt;em&gt;AND&lt;/em&gt; I started building some actual tools that (I hope) will be useful for CIR and the rest of the data journalism community. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, I do wish I had more assignments at CIR. I've been feeling underutilized, and I'd really like to be designing and building &lt;em&gt;systems&lt;/em&gt; rather than one-off graphics. Hopefully I can find my way onto a bigger project – or at the very least pick up some additional smaller ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="events"&gt;Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="visualizedpoliticaldata"&gt;Visualized: Political Data&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-fourth-month/../visualized-political-data/"&gt;I wrote about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="googleio2015"&gt;Google I/O 2015&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/io2015-note-dump/"&gt;I took some notes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="mentoringstanfordstudents"&gt;Mentoring Stanford Students&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a day at Stanford helping Cheryl Phillips’ computer science and journalism students design their data visualization projects. It was a cool experience, and I'm grateful for the opportunity to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="projects"&gt;Projects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id="publishedwherecanyoucarryaconcealedguninpublic"&gt;Published: Where can you carry a concealed gun in public?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-fourth-month/../the-third-month/#supersecretprojectno2"&gt;Super-Secret Project No. 2&lt;/a&gt; that I mentioned last month.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//www.revealnews.org/article/the-right-to-bear-arms-in-public-how-courts-have-ruled-so-far/#us_map"&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/06/us-map.jpg" alt="" title=""&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check it out:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//www.revealnews.org/article/the-right-to-bear-arms-in-public-how-courts-have-ruled-so-far/#us_map"&gt;U.S. Map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project strengths:&lt;/strong&gt;
I’m pretty happy with how this project turned out, especially from the technical implementation side of things. It’s quite small for an interactive (~157KB, almost half of which comes from Reveal web fonts and analytics); it’s responsive; it provides a tailored experience for touch devices; and the data is completely accessible via the keyboard &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; screen readers. I think it’s a good stab at making interactive graphics usable for a broader audience. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opportunities for improvement:&lt;/strong&gt;
I don’t love this interactive from a news value perspective – it's a bit superficial since most of the data isn’t geographic. Also, the addition of the court locations was a (very) late feature request, so that portion of the graphic doesn't work particularly well on mobile devices, just due to time constraints. There's definitely room to improve the newsroom's digital workflow processes; I have some ideas that I'll elaborate on at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="publishedcaliforniasconcealedgunpermitsbycounty"&gt;Published: California's Concealed Gun Permits by County&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;These interactives were part of &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-fourth-month/../the-third-month/#supersecretprojectno3"&gt;Super-Secret Project No. 3&lt;/a&gt; I mentioned last month.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//www.revealnews.org/article/want-to-carry-a-concealed-gun-live-in-sacramento-not-san-francisco/#ca_map"&gt;&lt;img src="http://julia67.github.io/content/images/2015/06/cali-map.jpg" alt="California Map" width="260px" style="float:right;margin:10px 0 20px 20px;padding:10px;left:30%;"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check 'em out:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//www.revealnews.org/article/want-to-carry-a-concealed-gun-live-in-sacramento-not-san-francisco/#ca_map"&gt;Choropleth Map&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//www.revealnews.org/article/want-to-carry-a-concealed-gun-live-in-sacramento-not-san-francisco/"&gt;Interactive Table&lt;/a&gt; (scroll down a bit)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project strengths:&lt;/strong&gt;
The graphics are lightweight and performant; the data is (mostly) accessible; the styles are on-brand; and the user experience on mobile isn't terrible. I also wrote all the interactivity in vanilla javascript, so the graphics are depedency-free, which is nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opportunities for improvement:&lt;/strong&gt;
A few notes on deadlines: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deadlines are important.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deadlines only work when they're communicated.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deadlines shouldn't move – they especially shouldn't move &lt;em&gt;up&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For these graphics, I had a bunch of accessibility enhancements I hoped to get in place before publication, but when (on June 11) the deadline moved from Tuesday, June 16 to Friday, June 12...certain features were cut. Ambigious deadlines are worthless – they don't allow people to appropriately prioritize their work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;/rant&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, now I'm trying to build some SVG generation tools that will automatically include accessiblility features (tab indexes, keyboard events, etc.) so that developers can include AT enhancements in their graphics without needing to budget extra time to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="awaitingpublicationsupersecretprojectno1"&gt;Awaiting Publication: Super-Secret Project No. 1&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is the same &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/the-fourth-month/../the-third-month/#supersecretprojectno1"&gt;Super-Secret Project No. 1&lt;/a&gt; that I talked about last month. I finished it around mid-May, but I'm not sure when it's scheduled for publication.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="newprojectaccessiblesvggenerator"&gt;New Project: Accessible SVG Generator&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like I mentioned above, I'm working on a front-end tool that will generate accessible SVG graphics. It'll be more of a resource for UI folks and ambitious reporters rather than back-end devs. I'm excited about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="news"&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My session proposal on SVG animation was accepted for &lt;a href="https://nejsconf.com/"&gt;NEJSConf&lt;/a&gt;. It's a single-track conference, so that'll be a new and exciting experience for me. This conference is also going to be awesome because: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's at the &lt;a href="http://www.omahazoo.com/"&gt;zoo&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io//twitter.com/beep"&gt;@beep&lt;/a&gt; is the keynote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I get to return to Homaha for it. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are all good things.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/the-fourth-month/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">3d1885eb-8d5e-4353-9b89-e5d81dde7d56</guid><category>opennews</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2015 23:43:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>#IO2015: Note dump</title><description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Select session notes from &lt;a href="https://events.google.com/io2015/"&gt;Google I/O 2015&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id="keynotewatchhttpsyoutube7vfigmdsme"&gt;Keynote (&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/7V-fIGMDsmE"&gt;Watch&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="androidm"&gt;Android M&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;App Permissions&lt;/strong&gt; – You can choose which permissions you can agree to. Defers asking until the point in the UX process when the permission is needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chrome Custom Tabs&lt;/strong&gt; – Resolves existing UX issues surrounding in-app browsers/webviews/native browsers. With Custom Tabs, the web view will open over the top of the app and inherit all of Chrome's features – security, passwords, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;App Linking&lt;/strong&gt; – Adds a namespace to the android manifest for verified links – so links are incorporated directly into the platform so they always open in the right application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile Payments&lt;/strong&gt; – Android Pay promises better UX, more security than Google Wallet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fingerprint Support&lt;/strong&gt; – Use fingerprint to authorize Android Pay transactions. Device unlock. Open authentication APIs so devs can incorporate fingerprint support to their own apps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Power &amp;amp; Charging&lt;/strong&gt; – Doze. Uses motion detection to put device into deeper sleep state. 2X performance improvements. The device can now act as charger for other devices with reverse USB.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UX Enhancements&lt;/strong&gt; – Better word selection and context menus. Direct share, simplified volume controls.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="androidwear"&gt;Android Wear&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1,500 watch faces for Android Wear &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Glanceable, actionable, effortless – all interactions should be this way, just like checking the time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always on screens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wrist gestures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Emoji recognizer – hand-draw emojis on the screen, and the watch will recognize the shape of drawing and translate it into emoji&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New launcher&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More than 4,000 apps have been developed for Android Wear so far&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="projectbrillomoreinfohttpsdevelopersgooglecombrillo"&gt;Project Brillo (&lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/brillo/"&gt;More Info&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brillo extends Android to connected devices for easy integration with your smartphone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weave is the standard IoT protocol that connects the phone to the device to the cloud&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="googlenow"&gt;Google Now&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goals:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Understand context (100m places, Natural language processing)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide answers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take action&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now on Tap
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provides in-context assistance without leaving the app you’re currently using&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="googlephotos"&gt;Google Photos&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pinch view to change time criteria&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Private auto organization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Groups photos of the same person over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unlimited storage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="globalefforts"&gt;Global Efforts&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There's a ton of low end phones in emerging markets, perhaps more than high end devices in established areas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google Translate – In emerging markets, the phone may be a person's first computer. Projected 1.2 billion smartphones by 2016.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Goal – Remove barriers of smartphone adoption with &lt;strong&gt;AndroidOne&lt;/strong&gt;. Create better devices for emerging markets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issues – Connectivity. Data. Speed. Size. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimized search results – 4x faster, 80% smaller data transfer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offline support for search results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offline maps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="developertools"&gt;Developer Tools&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Android Studio 1.3 – faster build speeds, full C++ support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Polymer 1.0 – material design web components&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cocoapods  – import google analytics, maps, etc into xcode for iOS development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud Test Labs for mobile app testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firebase – build an app worrying about the back end, provides asset management, authentication&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;App indexing – index app content in Google search results&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloud messaging – adding iOS support, topic subscriptions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mobile web – push notifications, add to home screen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Universal app campaigns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google play – conversion funnel snapshot, listing experiments (like optimizely, including app icon tests)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="virtualreality"&gt;Virtual Reality&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New Google Cardboard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expeditions – program for virtual reality field trips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionaccessibledesignguidelinesreadmorehttpgooglecomaccessibility"&gt;Session: Accessible Design Guidelines (&lt;a href="http://google.com/accessibility"&gt;Read more&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="whyisnteverythingaccessible"&gt;Why isn't everything accessible?&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it seems really hard.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="useheuristicevaluationtoimprovedesignsforaccessibility"&gt;Use heuristic evaluation to improve designs for accessibility&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on usability within accessibility
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Fonts can be enlarged&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Critical audio elements/sounds include text alternative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Touch targets should be large enough for a low mobility user&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="improvingthedesignprocess"&gt;Improving the design process&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diversify your personas &lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;include persons for low vision, low mobility, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;define the user journey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what are the steps to complete the task?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluate and prioritize &lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;choose your participant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;have a person with a disability help you or simulate your user's perspective&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organize the equipment &lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Acquire and learn the technology&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conduct the evaluation  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capture your process &lt;br&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Record the steps the user takes to complete the task&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share and inspire&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionaccessiblewebcomponentsrepohttpgithubcomwebcomponentsgoldstandardwiki"&gt;Session: Accessible Web Components (&lt;a href="http://github.com/webcomponents/gold-standard/wiki"&gt;Repo&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web components are exciting but create some challenges for accessibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 in 7 will experience a disability in their life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://github.com/webcomponents/gold-standard/wiki"&gt;http://github.com/webcomponents/gold-standard/wiki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a checklist for development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start with the keyboard.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Focusable. Put elements into the tab order. Add tabindex="0" attribute to give elements keyboard focus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visible focus state. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keyboard support. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test semantics with a screen reader.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Declared semantics. Look into accessibility nodes. Semantics: role, value, state. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Labels. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ARIA (accessible rich internet applications). The attribute "aria-label" can be added to elements that don't need a visual label. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Redundant color. Don't use color alone to distinguish between different elements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sufficient contrast. 4.5 minimum contrast ratio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developers need to build their own accessibility nodes into polymer web components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionadaptivedesignwithmaterial"&gt;Session: Adaptive Design with Material&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How we talk about taking about UI:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;To identify an element, we describe its structure, behavior, position, and permanence.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Breakpoints:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Show a single level of content hierarchy under 600px.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1600px is the max width with Material.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grids create limitations for a layout, and within those limitations come opportunities. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the new Chrome Developer Tools devices tab for testing layouts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionnextgenerationmobilewebwatchhttpsyoutubeizzdhtup5qg"&gt;Session: Next Generation Mobile Web (&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/iZZdhTUP5qg"&gt;Watch&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="reach"&gt;Reach&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reach of content – rediscovering the superpower of the web&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1B+ Chrome users&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="performance"&gt;Performance&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When is a site performant enough? When the user can't perceive it. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;strong&gt;RAIL&lt;/strong&gt; conceptual framework.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt; – Reaction Time &amp;lt;100ms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt; – Animation Time &amp;lt;16.67ms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&lt;/strong&gt; – Idle Time &amp;lt;50ms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L&lt;/strong&gt; – Load Time &amp;lt;1s&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="engagement"&gt;Engagement&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The missing piece&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push notifications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add to homescreen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offline support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sessiondevelopingappswithfirebasewatchhttpsyoutubewf9hzcqqi7a"&gt;Session: Developing Apps with Firebase (&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/wf9hZcqQI7A"&gt;Watch&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.firebase.com"&gt;Firebase&lt;/a&gt; is a cloud-based service that can “power your app's backend, including data storage, user authentication, static hosting, and more.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sky news UK election map was built on Firebase&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New at I/O – mobile offline support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionmakebelievedesigningforvr"&gt;Session: Make Believe: Designing for VR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtual reality is coming&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flow: Visual immersion --&gt; tracking --&gt; input --&gt; VR &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessibility:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;VR viewers anyone can make (Cardboard viewers)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visual immersion:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Focus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Depth perception&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Latency&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different lenses for each eye:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Pincushion distortion in one, barrel distortion in the other&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Input without controllers:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Capacitive triggers&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lessons learned:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;VR is great for exploring spaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great for empathy&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Core pillars in VR game design:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Agency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comfort (high fps, g force only down, positional reference, blink movement, forward only game, no screen freeze, only player movement, snap turning, static skybox, large cockpit)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Progression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tactile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Empowerment&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designing the environment
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get scale right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bug-free geometry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reward exploring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coherent world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Safe spaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Player warning&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;h2 id="sessiongetyourappintothegoogleindex"&gt;Session: Get your app into the Google index&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id="resources"&gt;Resources:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Android and iOS app indexing: &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/io2015-note-dump/g.co/appfirstindexing"&gt;g.co/appfirstindexing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;URL Shortener: &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/io2015-note-dump/g.co/urlshortener"&gt;g.co/urlshortener&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search Console: &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/io2015-note-dump/g.co/Searchconsole"&gt;g.co/searchconsole&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;App Indexing: &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/io2015-note-dump/g.co/appindexing"&gt;g.co/appindexing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionmaterialicons"&gt;Session: Material Icons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are material icons?
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Consistent design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suitable for all platforms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suitable for all purposes&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Resources:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Material Icon Library – &lt;a href="http://google.com/design/icons"&gt;google.com/design/icons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the repo – &lt;a href="http://github.com/google/material-design-icons"&gt;github.com/google/material-design-icons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Icon font features:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ligatures! So cool. You can just type the name of the icon and the font will ligature itself into the desired image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standard link tag with Google Web Fonts&lt;br&gt; &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;span class="material-icons"&amp;gt;menu&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionmaterialdesignlitereadmorehttpsdevelopersgooglecomwebtoolsmaterialdesignlite"&gt;Session: Material Design Lite (&lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/web/tools/material-design-lite/"&gt;Read more&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What?&lt;/strong&gt; A CSS and JS framework to achieve the Material Design aesthetic for web apps without Polymer. Made up of three parts:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Styles:&lt;/strong&gt; colors, typography&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Components:&lt;/strong&gt; buttons, switches, form elements, tabs, menus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Templates:&lt;/strong&gt; product pages, dashboards, cards, blogs&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why?&lt;/strong&gt; To bridge the gap between the material design spec and web apps. It allows developers to build web apps with standard front-end languages so they can support older browsers (and for whatever other reason). &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How?&lt;/strong&gt; Code will be open sourced in github. It will be available as bundled JS and CSS, essentially like a jQuery UI replacement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Support?&lt;/strong&gt; IE9 plus for components. IE10+ for templates. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When?&lt;/strong&gt; To be released at the end of June.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preview?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.getmdl.io/"&gt;getmdl.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;  

&lt;h2 id="sessionreachandreengage"&gt;Session: Reach and Re-engage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push Notifications for Android and all desktop platforms (not iOS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only works on HTTPS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three APIs:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Service worker (JavaScript when tab isn't open)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push messaging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notifications&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workflow: App JS (request notification permission) --&gt; Chrome --&gt; Google cloud messaging --&gt; app server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Debug with &lt;a href="chrome://serviceworker-internals"&gt;chrome://serviceworker-internals&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Not in regular Chrome Dev Tools yet&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;UX Principles:
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Only use it for really high priority things&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Track click through rate for notifications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Track when people revoke permissions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Users should demonstrate intent before sites ask for a permission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Airline example - after purchasing a ticket, show button asking if user is interested in receiving notifications, after user engage - then ask permission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow users to opt out&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For example, if the user wants updates on a story, they should be able to see an option to turn off notifications when they view the story again.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Recorded I/O 2015 Sessions: &lt;a href="https://events.google.com/io2015/videos"&gt;https://events.google.com/io2015/videos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/io2015-note-dump/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">29f251a8-c957-40ea-9711-6d51b4b20e88</guid><category>conf</category><category>google-io</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2015 23:45:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>4 topics from Visualized: Political Data</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I spent a couple days in DC last week so I could attend &lt;a href="http://visualized.com/politicaldata/"&gt;Visualized: Political Data&lt;/a&gt;, a one-day conference dedicated to exploring data visualizations in the context of political science, political campaigns, and political journalism. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt conflicted about flying all the way from SFO to DCA for a one-day event, but since political data viz is both where I came from (working with Gallup’s opinion poll data) and where I’d potentially like to go again, I figured it would be worth it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm glad I went. I was a little disappointed that some of the slated speakers had cancelled (including Lisa Strausfeld, who I had been looking forward to seeing), but overall the sessions were engaging and insightful. I definitely picked up some good info – the highlights of which I'll share with you now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="topic1publicdataopengovernment"&gt;Topic 1: Public Data / Open Government&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Derek Willis (NYT), Ryan Sibley (Sunlight Foundation), and Rebecca Williams (Data.gov) all tackled topics related to working with government data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Willis began with the example of collecting leave of absence records for congressional representatives. This is a metric that should be tracked and available but isn’t – either due to human error or bad record-keeping practices. Plus, even if we had accurate data on congressional leaves of absence, we still wouldn’t know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; a representative was absent. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while it’s nice to play with government datasets, you should really be looking beyond that – combining datasets from various places and scraping data from government apps to fill in the pieces. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Willis said the biggest opportunities for improvement are in: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing efficient information markets  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linking offline and online actions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improving speed and accuracy in public data reporting. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out some of Willis’ projects: &lt;a href="https://theunitedstates.io/"&gt;@unitedstates&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://openelections.net/"&gt;Open Elections&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sibley went over a few of the datasets that Sunlights has opened:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="politicalinfluence"&gt;Political influence:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://realtime.influenceexplorer.com/newest-filings/#?ordering=-filing_number&amp;amp;time_range=cycle"&gt;FEC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://sunlightfoundation.com/policy/municipal_campaign_finance/"&gt;State campaign finance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://reporting.sunlightfoundation.com/lobbying/"&gt;Lobbying data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunlightfoundation.com/search/?q=revolving+door&amp;amp;order_by=1"&gt;Revolving door data&lt;/a&gt; (also see &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/visualized-political-data/OpenSecrets.org"&gt;OpenSecrets.org&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://transparencycaucus.org"&gt;Advisor Committee on Transparency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="criminaljustice"&gt;Criminal justice:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://sunlightfoundation.com/criminaljustice/"&gt;Criminal justice data collection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sunlightfoundation.com/blog/2015/05/01/the-benefits-of-criminal-justice-data-beyond-policing/"&gt;Bureau of Justice Statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;U.S. Sentencing Commission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Local police departments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sibley also discussed some of the issues that make it hard to achieve Sunlight’s goals regarding open data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Methodologies can keep us from understanding the whole story. 
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Example: When requesting data on the cause of death by law enforcement, the CDC suppressed smaller numbers to protect individual identities.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Old technology stands in the way of improving reporting. 
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Example: Senators don’t disclose their campaign finance reports digitally at this time. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the criminal justice system, there’s no way to track individual cases over time because the police, courts, corrections, and re-entry organizations don’t share data with each other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In politics, there’s no way to track all the different players. 
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Example: There is no unique ID for donations by organization, so if a company’s name changes, it’s difficult to match it with its previous name. When unique IDs are missing, it’s hard to identify which organizations are affiliated.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help resolve some of these issues, Sibley implored everyone to use the data. Demonstrated interest will lead to the release of more and better data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Williams had similar things to say regarding government data collection – sometimes government data simply isn’t properly collected, structured, public, or reusable. This is where coalitions and partnerships between the government and the private sector (like &lt;a href="http://julia67.github.io/visualized-political-data/freelawfounders.org"&gt;freelawfounders.org&lt;/a&gt;) become valuable. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest advantage of government data is that you can vote on it. The more you can point to people losing money, the more actionable the response will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="links"&gt;Links:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://fedspendingtransparency.github.io/"&gt;http://fedspendingtransparency.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://labs.data.gov/dashboard/offices"&gt;http://labs.data.gov/dashboard/offices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="topic2maps"&gt;Topic 2: Maps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alicia Parlapiano (New York Times) and Alyson Hurt (NPR) both spoke about maps – mostly U.S. state maps. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alicia laid out four goals for representing state data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessibility  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fairness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revelation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “fairness problem” relates to how the physical size of different states can misrepresent the data by masking huge differences in population. Take national elections for example: Montana and Delaware have the same number of electoral votes (3), but when you look at a map, Montana’s size dwarfs Delaware’s, which – at a glance – leaves the impression that Montana’s votes count more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cartograms can help solve the fairness problem for electoral votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grid maps – made of squares or hexagons – are also good options when you want to show state totals without giving any one state more visual weight than another. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hurt explained that the challenge with grid maps is geographic fidelity. Consider offering context by placing a geographically accurate image next to the cartogram. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parlapiano and Hurt also emphasized that maps aren’t the only way to present state data – and they frequently aren’t even the best way. Jonathan Schwabish also touched on this point. He suggested asking four questions before choosing to make a map:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should it be a bar chart?  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should it be a scatterplot?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should it be a table?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should it simply be a sentence?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id="topic3elections"&gt;Topic 3: Elections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy Cotgreave (Tableau) and Sarah Newhall (Blue State Digital) spoke about using data visualization to engage people with political data. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contgreave specifically analyzed how the U.K. media used twitter in the recent elections. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="contgreavesdiscoveries"&gt;Contgreave's discoveries:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sentiment tracking is dangerous&lt;/strong&gt; – This is especially true with Twitter because Twitter demographics are not representative of the real world. However, Twitter stats are very shareable, and people take it for granted that the data is accurate. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Polls v. actual results&lt;/strong&gt; – For the UK election, none of the polls were correct. Even though the pollsters got it wrong, the poll results still drove the party strategy, the media, the agenda. Pollsters are sometime too shocked by outliers and will massage the data too much. In the most recent elections, the outliers weren’t really outliers at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer a new question every day&lt;/strong&gt; – Play with the data and post it on a day-to-day basis because that’s what keeps people engaged. If you build out all these fancy apps for visualizing – but the data is boring – people won’t stay interested. For example, if you’re visualizing trends over time but the trend never changes, no one will care.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newhall came at it from the marketing campaign side of things. She emphasized that data does a handful of things when used to influence people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It proves what’s at stake.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It motivates people to act.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It turns defense into offense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It shapes the narrative and provides clear explanations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It informs and inspires.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="topic4dataforhumans"&gt;Topic 4: Data for Humans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jamie Chandler (George Washington University), Jonathan Schwabish (Urban Institute), and Ben Casselman (FiveThirtyEight) &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="fromchandler"&gt;From Chandler:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today we have an opportunity to take data and communicate it to people in a simple, elegant way – and cut through all the talk that they get from the political world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data has been a big part of elections over the last couple cycles. We have all this data that’s being used to drive the vote, but we can also use that data in our messaging. We can communicate very complex things to the public in very simple ways. Simple data points that will shift our perception of previously held beliefs. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We’re missing the bridge between data science and communications. Politicians, CEOs, leaders rely on their gut feel 67% of the time. They’ll disregard what the data scientist recommends. Communications professionals have not be exposed to this level of sophistication [data analysis]. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the campaign world, we have to start thinking about how we connect the people who talk to the public and the people who do the analysis. Vocative is an online news agency that partners a data scientist with a journalist to mine the web for news. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If we’re going to bring data into the conversation, we have to remember who the average person is. In general, only 66% are able to remember visual. Statistical literacy is generally very low. People have biases when it relates to politics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="fromschwabish"&gt;From Schwabish:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think carefully and critically about your graphics – because people will learn something from them. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix Modalities
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Example: &lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/life/culturebox/2014/10/population_map_use_our_interactive_map_to_figure_out_how_many_flyover_states.html"&gt;Equal population mapper&lt;/a&gt; from Slate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Example: “The site now stores 90 million gallons of radioactive water, more than enough to fill Yankee stadium." - WashPo&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Big enough, but not too big
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Super-imposing Jupiter on Earth's horizon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steve Jobs presenting the Macbook Air in an envelope&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have a Soul
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Identifiable Victim Effect. We’re more likely to provide aid to an actual person.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The problem with statistics is that they don’t activate our moral emotions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communicating requires connecting.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="fromcasselman"&gt;From Casselman:&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reach readers who aren't data junkies? (Without disappointing the nerds)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communicate methodology? (Without convoluting the story)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reflect uncertainty? (Without sewing confusion)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Readers should be able to understand:
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Where the data comes from&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limitations of the data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The assumptions and decisions we've made while working with the data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How our analysis supports our conclusions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How confident we are in this conclusions&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes the uncertainty is the story itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;More coverage of &lt;em&gt;Visualized: Political Data:&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/search?src=typd&amp;amp;q=%23visualizedpd"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.azavea.com/blogs/atlas/2015/05/unicorns-ducks-and-things-that-are-big-a-recap-of-visualized-political-data/"&gt;Azavea report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><link>http://julia67.github.io/visualized-political-data/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">e7dc5fd7-736e-4844-87b9-e41507859188</guid><category>conf</category><dc:creator>Julia Smith</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2015 00:46:11 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>